[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Which manufacturing process includes the powder metallurgy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) casting",
            "b) forming and shaping",
            "c) machining",
            "d) joining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Forming and shaping process includes powder metallurgy. Powder metallurgy is a process in which material or shapes are made from or by using metal powders."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not included in forming and shaping process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rolling",
            "b) forging",
            "c) sheet forming",
            "d) broaching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Only rolling, forging and sheet forming are included in forming and shaping process. Broaching is included in fabrication process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Expendable mold and permanent mold are the parts of ____  manufacturing process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) machining",
            "b) casting",
            "c) none of the mentioned",
            "d) joining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In casting, we prepare a mould in which we pour liquid metal. Then we solidify the metal and make the product of desired shape with the help of pattern."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of the following is included in machining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) extrusion",
            "b) soldering",
            "c) drilling",
            "d) coating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Casting doesn’t includes grinding process. Machining process includes grinding process."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes are included in finishing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) honing and welding",
            "b) polishing and lapping",
            "c) coating and milling",
            "d) molding and plating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is a metal joining process. It joints the metal by melting and flowing a filler metal into the joint. The adjoining metal has higher melting point compare to filler metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of finishing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diffusion bonding",
            "b) burnishing",
            "c) both diffusion bonding and burnishing",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Drilling is included in machining process. For drilling, the drill is rotated with a downward pressure causing the tool to penetrate into the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of joining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) adhesive bonding",
            "b) brazing",
            "c) soldering",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coating and plating are included in finishing .Welding is included in joining, molding is included in casting                             and milling is included in machining. Rest all( mentioned ) are included in finishing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of permanent joining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) welding",
            "b) soldering",
            "c) both welding and soldering",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Forming and shaping type process include the process like drawing."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of temporary joining process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) brazing",
            "b) mechanical joining",
            "c) both brazing and mechanical joining",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only burnishing is an example of finishing process. Diffusion type bonding is included in the of process of joining."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "In ____type of manufacturing process, material is wasted. It is in the form of chips.",
        "Options": [
            "a) machining process",
            "b) casting process",
            "c) joining process",
            "d) forming and shaping process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adhesive bonding, brazing and soldering all are thetypes of joining process. In adhesive bonding, adhesive are used to manufacture an assembly. Brazing and soldering are also the type of manufacturing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Which type of metal is used in casting process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) liquid",
            "b) solid",
            "c) gas",
            "d) plastic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In casting, generally we used metal in liquid form so that it can be easily poured and then we solidified it."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Options": [
            "2. The casting can be defined as pouring of molten metal into a mould",
            "and taking it out after it becomes vapor.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false.In casting, first we take metal in liquid form, Then we pour it and after it we let it to solidify and then we take it out."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the component of foundry sand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) river sand",
            "b) clay",
            "c) moisture",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all are the components of foundry sand. Permeability is the important property for sand casting and this property is totally related with the foundry sand.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Why the porous structure provided by the silica is necessary in casting process?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  for the escape of gases",
            "b) for the escape of vapors",
            "c) for the escape of both gases and vapors",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silica has a property to withstand high temperature. Silica sand is taken out by crushing sandstone. It is mostly used because of its great abundance."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which of the following provide cohesion among the sand particles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) clay and moisture",
            "b) clay and silica",
            "c) moisture and silica",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Permeability is the important factor for sand casting. If we do not allow gases and vapor to escape from the mould it can damage the casting pattern and can also weaken the strength of the material. Silica allows the escape of gases and vapor and that’s why it is necessary to provide this porous structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which of the following component gives the necessary plasticity to sand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) silica",
            "b) clay",
            "c) moisture",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The upper portion of casting flask is known as cope where as lower portion of casting flask is known as drag."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "In forging process, metals are shaped by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) impact",
            "b) cohesion",
            "c) tense",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Forging is a manufacturing process which shapes the metal with the help of localized compressive force. It shapes metal with impact force."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Which method is considered as one of the oldest methods of giving required shapes to the metals ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) casting",
            "b) forging",
            "c) forming",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Experts considered forging as the oldest method of giving required shapes. For a long time, this forging was used by the smith with hammer. After that, this method was cam into picture in industries. "
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the example of impact pressure forging ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) striking a blow",
            "b) shaping by press",
            "c) all of the mentioned",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. It gives greater strength and also chances of voids are reduced in this type of forging."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which type of forging is done by deforming the metal at room temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cold forging",
            "b) simply forging",
            "c) hot forging",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Striking a blow is an example of impact pressure and shaping by press is an example of squeeze pressure forging."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Which type of forging is done by blacksmith?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hand forging",
            "b) machine forging",
            "c) both hand forging and machine forging",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Hot forging is known as simply forging."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "For which purpose, hand forging is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) maintenance work",
            "b) production of small articles tools",
            "c) repair work",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cold forging is done by deforming the metal at room temperature. This is done by increasing the level of stress above the elastic limit."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "In which forging process, parts are heated in open hearth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) machine forging",
            "b) hand forging",
            "c) both hand forging and machine forging",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Hot forging is also known as simply forging and metal is heated to the temperature(up to plastic temperature) in this process."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "In which forging process, parts are heated in closed hearth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) machine forging",
            "b) hand forging",
            "c) hand forging and machine forging both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This forging makes increment in the diameter of the workpiece by compressing its length. Engine parts, coupling, bolts etc. are produced with the help of upset forging."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Roll forging is done with the help of______",
        "Options": [
            "a) cylindrical rolls",
            "b) semi-cylindrical roll",
            "c) both cylindrical and semi cylindrical rolls",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hand forging is done in the smithy shop. This hand forging is done with the help of hand tools or steam hammer."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Which type of process is also known as fabrication process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) casting",
            "b) forming",
            "c) joining",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Joining process is also known as the fabrication process. In fabrication process, product is made from raw materials and not from ready made components."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which type of manufacturing process can fabrication process be termed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) primary",
            "b) secondary",
            "c) tertiary",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fabrication process is also known as secondary manufacturing process. Fabrication process doesn’t produce raw material. It produce products from raw materials. That’s why it is known as secondary process."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is not included in fabrication process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) welding",
            "b) riveting",
            "c) pressing",
            "d) surface finish"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Welding, riveting and pressing are included in fabrication process, Where as surface finish is included in machining process."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following pair is the part of fabrication process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) welding and metal removal",
            "b) brazing and sintering",
            "c) cohesion and sintering",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metal removal is the type of machining process and cohesion is  included in casting process. Rest are included in fabrication process."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which of the following fabrication process is mainly responsible for the fabrication of very high pressure boilers and nuclear reactors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) welding",
            "b) sintering",
            "c) brazing",
            "d) pressing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Invention of welding has made a revolution in the fabrication process. Complex fabrication processes are also possible because of welding."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of conventional welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gas welding",
            "b) friction welding",
            "c) resistance welding",
            "d) air welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only gas welding and resistance welding are the types of conventional welding. friction welding is the type of recent welding process."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of gas welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) atomic hydrogen arc welding",
            "b) shielded metal arc welding",
            "c) inert gas arc welding",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: None of them is type of gas welding. All are included in welding process of type air welding."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of the recent welding process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) laser beam",
            "b) friction",
            "c) ultrasonic",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Spot welding and seam welding are included in resistance welding according to the classification of welding."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Oxy acetylene welding and oxy-hydrogen welding are the examples of ____ welding.",
        "Options": [
            "a) gas",
            "b) air",
            "c) resistance",
            "d) friction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all are the types of recent welding process base on the classification of welding process. These all are high accurate welding process with better production rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "In which operation, motion of job is rotary and motion of cutting tool is forward translating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) turning",
            "b) planning",
            "c) milling",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Turning is done when motion of job is rotary and motion of cutting tool is forward translating. In turning operation, metal is removed from the outer diameter of the surface. It is very basic operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which type of job motion is there in drilling operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rotary",
            "b) translating",
            "c) fixed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Motion of job is fixed in drilling operation. The drilling machine is one of the most important machine tool in workshop after lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "In which type of operation, motion of cutting tool is translating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling and milling",
            "b) milling and turning",
            "c) boring and drilling",
            "d) turning and planning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Motion of cutting tool is translating in case of boring and milling. Boring is generally performed to enlarge the holes which are previously made and milling is generally performed to remove the material from the metal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "In which type of operation, motion of cutting tool is rotary as well as translating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) planning",
            "b) milling",
            "c) drilling",
            "d) turning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In drilling, both type of motion of cutting tool is necessary. For drilling, the drill is rotated with a downward pressure causing the tool to penetrate into the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Which type of cutting tools have wide application on lathes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single point",
            "b) multi point",
            "c) both single point and multi point",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. In drilling, motion of job is fixed."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the example of multi point cutting tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) milling cutter",
            "b) broaching tool",
            "c) both milling utter and broaching tool",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Motion of cutting tool is intermittent translating in milling operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "In how many groups, cutting tools can be divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Single point cutting tools have wide application on slotting machines. Shear tools, boring tools, planner tools etc. are the examples of single point cutting tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of non cutting shaping process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) turning",
            "b) forging",
            "c) drilling",
            "d) milling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Milling cutter and broaching tools use multi point cutting tool to perform their operations. In milling, material is removed as the work is fed against a rotating multipoint cutter. Broaching also remove material but high accuracy. Although its cost is high, it is largely used."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the example of cutting shaping process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) knurling",
            "b) forging",
            "c) pressing",
            "d) drawing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cutting tools can be classified in two groups : single point cutting tools and multi point cutting tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "In how many groups, various metal working processes can be classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Motion of job is forward translating in broaching operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Why metal removal process is costly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) more energy is required",
            "b) some of the material is wasted",
            "c) both more energy is required and some of the material is wasted",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As we require more energy, cost will definitely increase and again some material is also removed(lost) in this process."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "In which machining process, removed metal is negligible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) surface finishing",
            "b) metal removal",
            "c) both surface finishing and metal removal",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Metal which is removed, is more (can’t negligible) in case of metal removal process but in surface finishing metal removal is negligible."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is not grouped under metal removal process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) boring",
            "b) milling",
            "c) tumbling",
            "d) rolling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Accuracy of dimension is not affected in surface finishing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not groped under the surface finishing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) sawing",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) buffing",
            "d) polishing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Only boring and milling are grouped under metal removal process. Tumbling is the type of surface finishing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "In how many groups, metal removal process can be classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only tapping, buffing and polishing are grouped under surface finishing process. Sawing is the type of metal removal process."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "In which type of metal removal process, grinding is included?",
        "Options": [
            "a) conventional machining",
            "b) abrasive process",
            "c) nontraditional machining",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Metal removal process gives poor contour on the compound."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "______ metal removal process includes milling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) conventional machining",
            "b) abrasive process",
            "c) nontraditional machining",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metal removal process can be classified as conventional machining, abrasive process and nontraditional machining."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "In which type of metal removal process, thermal energy is included?",
        "Options": [
            "a) conventional machining",
            "b) abrasive process",
            "c) nontraditional machining",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the classification of metal removal process, it is included in abrasive process. When we remove metal with the help of single or multiple abrasive particle, the process is called abrasive process."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of nontraditional machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) turning",
            "b) drilling",
            "c) milling",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the classification of metal removal process, it is included in conventional process. Conventional machines are machines which requires human efforts and that are not fully automated. Metal removal process need some human efforts."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "In which metal removal process, material is removed by particles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) conventional machining",
            "b) abrasive process",
            "c) nontraditional machining",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is included in nontraditional machining. Thermal energy is an energy which is generated from the heat like kinetic energy of molecule, chemical energy of particle and so on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "In which process, various energy forms other than sharp cutting tool is used to remove materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) conventional machining",
            "b) abrasive process",
            "c) nontraditional machining",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Turning, drilling and milling are the types of nontraditional machining. Drilling means make a hole by using drilling machine and milling machine is a machine tool that removes metal as the work is fed against multipoint cutter. Turning is basic operation generally carried out on lathe machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of nontraditional  machining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) electrochemical process",
            "b) chemical machining",
            "c) mechanical energy process",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It can be understood from the definition of abrasive process. Like in abrasive water jet operation, material is removed by erosion."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Which of the following is included in basic machine tools?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lathe machine",
            "b) production milling machine",
            "c) production drilling machine",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the definition of basic type of machine tools, lathe is basic machine tool while production milling machine and production drilling machines are special purpose drilling machines."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Which type of machine tool is used for mass production of essentially small parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) general purpose",
            "b) special purpose",
            "c) automatic screw cutting",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The automatic type of screw cutting is used for this purpose. The automatic screw cutting is used because of its high accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which of the following does all the work of lathe machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) turning centre of CNC type",
            "b) machining centre of CNC type",
            "c) turning centre of CNC type and machining centre of CNC type both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This type of turning centre does most of jobs of lathe. Lathe is a basic machine used for producing cylindrical machine. It is considered as father of machine tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "CNC machining centre does all the work_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) milling machine",
            "b) drilling machine",
            "c) both milling and drilling machine",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CNC machining centre perform almost all jobs of milling and drilling machines. Drilling machine is used to produce holes and milling machines remove metal as the work is fed against a rotating multipoint cutter."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of lathe machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) capstan",
            "b) turret",
            "c) both capstan and turret",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These both are categorized under the types of lathe machine. Turret and capstan lathe are generally used for the production of duplicate parts"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "DNC stands for_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) digital numerical control",
            "b) direct numerical control",
            "c) double numerical control",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the history of machine tools, Egyptians were the first, who used that. They used the cylinder."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Machine tools can be classified as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) geometric shape of the work piece",
            "b) number of the work piece",
            "c) function of the machine",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNC is the abstract form of direct numerical control."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Options": [
            "12. The demand of instruments or parts, which are used for",
            "purpose of measurements are more in NC machine tool.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Machine tools are only economical, when it is used for producing small number of pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Which machine tool is known as the mother machine tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drill",
            "b) milling",
            "c) lathe",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lathe is known as the mother machine tool because it\ncan perform various type of operations. It is a versatile machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Lathe is primarily used for producing ____surfaces.",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat",
            "b) curve",
            "c) taper",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lathe is primarily used for producing cylindrical surfaces. But today it can perform various operations and perform various surfaces like curvilinear surface, flat surface and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which type of surface is produced by turning operation in lathe machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat",
            "b) cylindrical",
            "c) taper",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cylindrical surface is produced by turning operation in lathe machine. This turning can be done on the external surface. Boring is a type of turning which is performed in the internal surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "What is the necessary condition for turning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) material of work piece should be harder than the cutting tool",
            "b) cutting tool should be harder than the material of work piece",
            "c) hardness of the cutting tool and material of of piece should be same",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cutting tool should be harder than the material of work piece, so that it can be able to cut the work piece into the desire shape."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Traversing of tool parallel to the axis of job is termed as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) cross feed",
            "b) longitudinal feed",
            "c) both cross feed and traversing feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the definition of longitudinal feed. Similarly, traversing of tool perpendicular to the axis of job is known as cross feed."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Which type of feed is needed in facing operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal",
            "b) cross",
            "c) both cross and longitudinal",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. Swing diameter over the lathe is the largest diameter of work over the bed that will revolve without touching height of the centres measured from the bed of the lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which type of surface is produced in facing operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cylindrical",
            "b) taper",
            "c) flat",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Lathe is a versatile machine tool. It can produce holes, flat surfaces and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "In taper operation, which type of surface is produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat",
            "b) curve",
            "c) circular",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Facing operation is done by the cross feed. In facing, workpiece is rotated against the single point cutting tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Which type of feed is needed in turning operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal",
            "b) cross",
            "c) both cross and longitudinal",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flat surface is produced in facing operation as per the definition. In facing operation, metal is removed by the tool from thee end of the metal and flat surface is produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Which type of surface can be produced by lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat",
            "b) cylindrical",
            "c) curvilinear",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Traversing of tool at any angle to the job axis produces taper surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which type of lathe is also known as centre lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) engine lathe",
            "b) bench lathe",
            "c) room lathe",
            "d) capstan lathe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Engine lathe is also known as the centre lathe. This centre lathe is generally used for the production of cylindrical surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Wheel lathe is the type of ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) engine lathe",
            "b) centre lathe",
            "c) speed lathe",
            "d) special purpose lathe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  d\nExplanation: Wheel lathe is the type of special purpose lathe. This lathe is generally used for the purpose of turning wheels of railways locomotives and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Wood working lathe is the type of ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) engine lathe",
            "b) centre lathe",
            "c) speed lathe",
            "d) special purpose lathe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wood lathe is the type of speed lathe. Speed lathe can revolve spindle with great speed. It is also used for turning small objects."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Geared lathe is the type of____",
        "Options": [
            "a) engine lathe",
            "b) centre lathe",
            "c) speed lathe",
            "d) special purpose lathe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Geared lathe is the type of engine lathe. Engine lathe is a screw cutting type lathe. It has back-geared cone-driven headstock."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Belt driven lathe is the type of____",
        "Options": [
            "a) engine lathe",
            "b) centre lathe",
            "c) speed lathe",
            "d) special purpose lathe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Belt driven lathe is the type of centre lathe. In practical, various types of belt driven machines are used like V belt driven machine and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Duplicating lathe is the type of____",
        "Options": [
            "a) engine lathe",
            "b) centre lathe",
            "c) speed lathe",
            "d) special purpose lathe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per the classification of lathe, duplicating lathe the type of special purpose lathe. It is rarely used."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Spinning lathe is the type of____",
        "Options": [
            "a) engine lathe",
            "b) centre lathe",
            "c) speed lathe",
            "d) special purpose lathe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Spinning lathe is the type of speed lathe. Spinning lathe is a lathe generally used the purpose of shaping metal holloware with the help of flat stock over a form (of revolving type) with the help of hand tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of engine lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) centering lathe",
            "b) individual motor driven lathe",
            "c) duplicating lathe",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Centering lathe is the example of speed lathe and duplicating lathe  is the type of special purpose lathe while individual motor driven lathe is an example of engine lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following is special purpose lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) polishing lathe",
            "b) centering lathe",
            "c) spinning lathe",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polishing lathe, centering lathe and spinning lathe are the examples of speed lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the example of speed lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) wheel lathe",
            "b) polishing lathe",
            "c) gap bed lathe",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wheel lathe and gap bed lathe are the examples of the special purpose lathe while polishing lathe is an example of speed lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bench lathe",
            "b) tool room lathe",
            "c) capstan and turret lathe",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. T – lathe is the example of special purpose lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Lathe can be classified on the basis of_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) designs and construction",
            "b) fundamental principle",
            "c) function performance",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all are the types of lathe as per the lathe classification. Lathe is primarily intended for the purpose of producing cylindrical surfaces although today it becomes a versatile tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the base of the lathe machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bed",
            "b) tailstock",
            "c) headstock",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bed is the base of the lathe machine. This provides the necessary working height for the lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of the following is fitted on the bed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) headstock",
            "b) tailstock",
            "c) headstock and tailstock both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These both are fitted on the bed as per the definition. This is the structure on which the entire lathe parts are situated."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of the bed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vee slide",
            "b) tailstock",
            "c) carriage",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Actually, the bed generally rest on cast iron or welded structure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Which of the following provides foundation for the whole machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tailstock",
            "b) bed",
            "c) headstock",
            "d) carriage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are the part of the bed. Tailstock is a sliding unit on the bed-ways of the lathe bed. Carriage is the part of the lathe which slides over the bed-ways."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Which type of bed design offers more rigidity and thermal stability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) true slant bed",
            "b) flatbed",
            "c) conventional bed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the definition of the bed. It is the base of lathe which provides needed height as well as foundation for whole machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "In which slant angles, the slant bed design is offered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 and 60",
            "b) 60 & 45",
            "c) 30, 60 and 45",
            "d) 30 and 45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Generally, small lathes don’t need a sliding bed. Very large lathes have a sliding bed."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the part of bed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vee slide",
            "b) machine ways",
            "c) headstock",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the definition of the bed. The headstock is a fixed unit of the lathe on the left hand side of the lathe bed."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the advantages of cone pulley drive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) easy to maintain",
            "b) can take up heavy load",
            "c) positive drive when the back gear is in engagement.",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all are the advantages of the cone pulley drive. It is stepped pulley mounted on the main spindle which is free to revolve."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Options": [
            "2. Number of spindle speeds is limited to the number of steps",
            "in the cone pulley drive.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the definition of cone pulley drive. This cone pulley gets the drive from the main motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "What does happen during the overload in the cone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) number of steps in cone pulley increases",
            "b) belt slips off",
            "c) nothing happens",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the overload in the cone, the belt slips off so that no major damage happens to the lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Cone pulley drive without back gear arrangement means_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) back gear in",
            "b) back gear out",
            "c) back gear neutral",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. In practical work, it takes time to change the spindle speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Cone pulley drive with back gear arrangement means_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) back gear in",
            "b) back gear out",
            "c) back gear neutral",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the definition of the back gear. The headstock having cone pulley drive is known as cone pulley headstock."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which of the following mounted on the bush bearing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) speed motor",
            "b) spindle",
            "c) both spindle and speed motor",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the definition of the back gear. The axis of this back gear shaft is parallel to the axis of the main spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "The back gear unit has a shaft, which carries _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) a gear",
            "b) a pinion",
            "c) a gear and a pinion both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the construction of lathe, spindle is fitted on the bush bearing. It is mounted in the headstock casting and a gear wheel called bull gear is keyed to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "The axis of the back gear is_____ to the axis of the main spindle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) at any angle other than 0 and 90",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Stepped pulley is free to revolve."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "The top cover of all gear drive is_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) removable",
            "b) non-removable",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mentioned sentence is true for all gear drive as per the definition of it. The headstock having all gear drive is known as all-geared headstock."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "All gear drive is equipped with_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) clutches",
            "b) a brake",
            "c) clutches and a brake both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The top cover of all gear drive is removable if needed. All gear drive is like a box section of lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Sliding gears may be mounted on_____ intermediate shafts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only one",
            "b) only two",
            "c) two or more than two",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All gear drive is equipped with these both clutches and a bark. Clutch is a device which is used to connect and disconnect an engine and power transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which of the following operates the forks of the sliding gears?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lever",
            "b) spindle",
            "c) clutch",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. All gear drive has internal webs for shaft bearing and some other purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of having webs in all gear drive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) for stiffening",
            "b) for taking shaft bearings",
            "c) for stiffening and taking shaft bearing both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Actually, input shaft is connected by means of V belts to the main motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding the all gear drive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the headstock having all gear drive is known as all geared headstock",
            "b) the nose of the spindle is designed to accommodate the work holding devices",
            "c) the nose of the spindle is inside the headstock casting",
            "d) tone of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There may be two or more intermediate shafts on which sliding gears are mounted. It has an input shaft which is connected by means of V belts to the main motor."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding tailstock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tailstock is also known as loose headstock",
            "b) it is a fixed unit on the bed ways",
            "c) it provides support to the other end of the work when it is being machined",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The all above mentioned statements are correct except one which says that it is a fixed unit on the bed ways. Actually, it is a sliding unit on the bed ways"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "For performing which kind of operations, it ( tailstock ) holds a tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) reaming",
            "c) tapping",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tail stock holds a tool for performing operations such as drilling, reaming, tapping etc. To accommodate different lengths of work, the body of the tailstock can be adjusted along the ways chiefly by sliding it to the desired position."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "The body of the tailstock can be adjusted by clamping with the help of_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) bolts",
            "b) plates",
            "c) bolts and plates both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The body of the tailstock can be adjusted by clamping with the help of bolts and plates to adjust with job’s dimensions. The body of tailstock is situated on the right hand side of the lathe bed."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "The upper casting of the body can be moved_____ from the operator.",
        "Options": [
            "a) toward",
            "b) away",
            "c) toward or away both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The upper casting of the body can be moved toward or away from the operator. This movement is done with the help of setover screw to offset the tailstock for taper turning and to realign the tailstock centers for straight turning."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of spindle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) dead center",
            "b) hand wheel",
            "c) setover screw",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All above mentioned are the parts of spindle. In tailstock, the spindle holds dead center. In headstock, the spindle is able to hold live center."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Offset of tailstock is done for_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) taper turning",
            "b) straight turning",
            "c) both turning of taper type and straight type",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Offset is done for the purpose of taper turning. Taper is a shape in which the diameter of the both ends are different."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Realign of tailstock center is done for_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) taper turning",
            "b) straight turning",
            "c) taper turning and straight turning",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Realign is done for the purpose of straight turning. The body is bored to act as the barrel which carries the tailstock spindle that moves in and out of the barrel by means of a screw when the tailstock hand wheel is turned."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Which of the following is supported by the headstock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) spindle",
            "b) spindle bearing",
            "c) speed change mechanism",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Headstock is a fixed unit. It provides mechanical means of rotating the work at multiple speeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used to vary the speed of a lathe spindle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gear out",
            "b) gear in",
            "c) both gear out and gear in",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all are supported by the headstock."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Which type of end does tapered bar has?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pointed",
            "b) projected",
            "c) pointed or projected",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. It is not solid. The spindle is hollow in headstock and it is supported by the headstock."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Spindle is fitted with_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) chucks",
            "b) faceplates",
            "c) chucks or faceplates",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Spindle holds live centers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "The spindle was directly driven by_____ in later machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat belt pulley",
            "b) gear box",
            "c) flat belt pulley and gear box both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These both methods are used to vary the speed of the lathe. Apart from these two, variable speed motor is also used to vary the speed of a lathe spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "The spindle was directly driven by_____ in older machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat belt pulley",
            "b) gear box",
            "c) flat belt pulley and gear box both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Taper bar may has pointed or projected end depending upon the task. Tapered bar is a bar which has different diameters at both ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "In how many parts, compound rest can be classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compound rest can be classified in two parts : swivel base and top slide."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "The swivel base is assembled to the_____ of cross slide.",
        "Options": [
            "a) top",
            "b) middle",
            "c) bottom",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The swivel bas is always assembled to the top of the cross slide as per the construction of the lathe. The compound rest may be clamped at any desired position by tightening the T-bolts."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "How many types of movements are possible in carriage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three types of feed are possible in carriage. Longitudinal feed, cross feed and angular feed are possible in case of the carriage."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which type of operation is possible for the top slide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) manual",
            "b) by power feed",
            "c) manual and by power feed both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only manual operation is possible for the cross feed. The top slide assists in feeding the tool to the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which type of feed is always done perpendicular to the axis of work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal feed",
            "b) angular feed",
            "c) cross feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cross feed is always done perpendicular to the axis of the work as per the classification of carriage movements. Cross feed is done with the help of the cross-slide movement."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for compound rest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the swivel base is provided with a dovetail on its bottom surface",
            "b) the top slide has dovetail groove",
            "c) the assembly of the top slide to the swivel base is done by a tapered jib",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the sentences are true except the one which says that the swivel base is provided with a dovetail on its bottom surface. The swivel base is provided with a dovetail on its top surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "In compound rest, the screw-rod is fitted with_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) a hand wheel",
            "b) a graduated collar",
            "c) a hand wheel and a graduated collar both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Taper jib can be adjusted to control top slide movements."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which type of feed is necessary for the function of the cross slide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hand feed",
            "b) automatic feed",
            "c) either by hand feed or by automatic feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the sentences are true except the one which says that the top of the cross slide has got a dovetail groove machined. The bottom of the cross slide has got a dovetail groove machined."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Carriage provides various movements for the cutting tool______",
        "Options": [
            "a) manually",
            "b) by power feed",
            "c) manually and by power feed both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These two types of movements are possible in carriage. Carriage provides various movements for the cutting tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "The compound rest may be clamped at_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 degree",
            "b) 90 degree",
            "c) 180 degree",
            "d) any degree between 0 and 360"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the function of carriage. It can be locked on the bed at any desired position by tightening the carriage lock-screw."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which type of feed is always done parallel to the axis of work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal feed",
            "b) cross feed",
            "c) angular feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Compound rest may be clamped at any required position between 0 and 360 degree. It can be tightened by T-bolts at that position."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Which of the following assists in feeding the tool to the work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) swivel base",
            "b) top slide",
            "c) swivel base and top slide both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Longitudinal feed is always done parallel to the axis of the work as per the classification of carriage movements."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Which type of feed is done with the help of compound slide movement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal feed",
            "b) angular feed",
            "c) cross feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only top slide assists in feeding the tool to the work. We can give manual operation in the top slide."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "In how many parts, carriage can be divided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Angular feed is done with the help of the compound slide movement positioned at an angle to the axis of the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Saddle is_____ shaped casting and has_____ guide grooves and flat grooves.",
        "Options": [
            "a) H and V",
            "b) V and H",
            "c) H and H",
            "d) V and V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Carriage can be divided in saddle, cross-slide, compound rest swivel and top slide, tool post and apron."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "In saddle, grooves are machined at the ______ corresponding to the lathe bed ways.",
        "Options": [
            "a) top face",
            "b) middle face",
            "c) bottom face",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Saddle is H shaped casting and has v guide grooves and flat grooves. Saddle is mounted on the spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The cross slide functions_____ to the lathe axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) anti-parallel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In saddle, grooves are machined at the bottom corresponding to the lathe bed ways. The surface of the bed in contact with the sliding units of the lathe are known as guideways or slideways or bedways."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the part of single way tool post?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ring base",
            "b) rocket arm",
            "c) a tool clamping screw",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tool post is assembled to the top slide. The tool post holds the tool or tools meant for operations to be performed on the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "In single way tool post, the center height of the tool tip can be adjusted with the help of_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) rocket arm",
            "b) ring base",
            "c) rocket arm and ring base both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Single way tool post consists of these all parts. This tool post is consist of a circular tool post body with a slot for accommodating the tool or tool holder."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Four bolt tool post is held in position by____ straps and _____ bolts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 and 4",
            "b) 4 and 2",
            "c) 2 and 2",
            "d) 4 and 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. The ring base, a rocket arm and a tool clamping screw complete the assembly of this type of tool post. "
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Open slide tool post is clamped in position by_____ set screws.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both rocket arm and ring base are used for this purpose. The rigidity of the tool is less as it is clamped with only one bolt."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "In which tool post, quick replacement of the tool is ensured?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single way tool post",
            "b) four bolt tool post",
            "c) open slide tool post",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is held by 2 straps and 4 bolts. This type of tool post provides a very firm support for either a single or double tool set-up. This is, therefore, often fitted to heavy duty lathes."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Four way tool post is also known as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) square tool post",
            "b) indexing type tool post",
            "c) square tool post and indexing type tool post both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Loosing coil springs are fitted on each bolt to keep the straps in place. Adjustment of the tool height can be made by using parallel packing strips under the tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Four bolt tool post provides a very firm support for_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) single tool set up",
            "b) double tool set up",
            "c) either single or double tool set up",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Open slide tool post is clamped in position by 2 set screws. This tool is held quite independent of the main fixing bolt. "
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for four way tool post?",
        "Options": [
            "a) each tool is secured in the tool post by one bolt",
            "b) square head is clamped with the help of the locking lever",
            "c) it takes more time to set the center height",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In open slide tool post, the tool post slide can be swiveled to any desired position after loosening the central bolt which slides in a T-slot."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Options": [
            "15. Frequent changing of the tool for different operations need",
            "not be done in four way tool post.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These both terms square tool post and indexing type tool post are used as the synonyms of the four way tool post. Four tools can be fixed in this types of tool post and any one can be bought to the operating position and the square head is clamped with the help of the locking lever."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the following contains friction clutches?",
        "Options": [
            "a) saddle",
            "b) cross slide",
            "c) swivel base",
            "d) apron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Apron includes friction clutches. Friction clutches are there in apron for the purpose of automatic feeding."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The layout of the_____ includes an interlocking device.",
        "Options": [
            "a) saddle",
            "b) cross slide",
            "c) apron",
            "d) swivel base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The layout of the apron includes an interlocking tool which prevents or stops the simultaneous engagement of feed shaft and the lead screw."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The apron hand wheel can be turned to move carriage back and forth longitudinally with the help of hand. The complementary motion to this is obtained by______  handle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal feed",
            "b) cross feed",
            "c) angular feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The complementary motion to this is obtained by the cross feed handle which moves the cross slide and forth across the saddle."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "In apron, which type of feed is used to operate the carriage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hand feed",
            "b) power feed",
            "c) hand feed and power feed both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both type of feed is used to operate the carriage. Although hand feed takes more time and gives less accuracy while power feed takes less time and gives more accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "In which position, the section lever can be kept?",
        "Options": [
            "a) up and down",
            "b) up, down and neutral",
            "c) only neutral",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The section lever can be kept in all above mentioned positions to handle the feed. This apron is a part of lathe hangs over the front of the feed."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "With the help of how many half nuts, apron provide power feed to the carriage at the time of thread cutting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally 2 half nuts are used for this purpose. In addition, there is a split nut which engages when required with the lead screw, when cutting either internal or external thread."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "In Apron, power is transmitted from spindle to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) lead screw",
            "b) feed rod",
            "c) lead screw and feed rod both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power is transmitted to both lead screw and feed rod from spindle. The layout of this apron includes an interlocking device which prevents the simultaneous engagement of the feed shaft and the lead screw."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "Which of the following mechanism is used for the purpose of power transmission from the spindle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) spindle gear arrangement",
            "b) tumbler gear arrangement",
            "c) spindle gear arrangement and tumbler gear arrangement both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These both gear arrangements are used for the purpose of power transmission. In addition to this, there is hand wheel in apron which can be turned to move carriage back and forth longitudinally by hand for manual power."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Which of the following is suspended from the saddle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) apron",
            "b) gear box",
            "c) tool post",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. A warm is fixed on the feed rod with the help of the sliding key."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Which type of feeding does feed mechanism enables?",
        "Options": [
            "a) automatic",
            "b) manual",
            "c) automatic and manual both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Feed mechanism enables automatic feed. It enables feeding for the tool longitudinal and traversely whenever needed."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which of the following indicates the benefit of automatic feeding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the finish on the work will be better",
            "b) the feeding of the tool will be at a nonuniform continuous rate",
            "c) accuracy will be more",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All sentences are true except the one which says that the feeding of the tool will be at a nonuniform continuous rate. Actually, the feeding of the tool will be at a uniform continuous rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the part of feed mechanism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) spindle gear",
            "b) tumbler gear unit",
            "c) apron mechanism",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Manual feed requires more time for finishing the work. Automatic feed requires less time to finish the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "What happen if feed increases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cutting time increases",
            "b) cutting time decreases",
            "c) no effect on cutting time",
            "d) none of the mentioned."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are the parts of feed mechanism. Apart from spindle gear, tumbler gear unit and apron mechanism, there are some other parts like fixed stud gear, change gear unit, quick change gear box and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Increased feed_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases tool’s life",
            "b) decreases tool’s life",
            "c) no effect on tool’s life",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is work. Feed mechanism removes the need of manual labor. It works automatically. "
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not the part of the feed mechanism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fixed stud gear",
            "b) quick change gear box",
            "c) feed shaft",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the definition of the feed. This feed is also expressed in mm/revolution. In british system, it is expressed in inch per revolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "The feed mechanism enables feed for the tool______ whenever needed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinally",
            "b) traversely",
            "c) longitudinal and traversely both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Increased feed always reduces the cutting time. As the feed is increased, the speed of the cutting is increased and as the speed of the cutting is increased, its time will definitely decreased."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "How many main type of centres are there in lathe (most commonly)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Most commonly two types of centres are there in lathe : live and dead centres."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of centre in lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) live centre",
            "b) neutral centre",
            "c) dead centre",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only live centre and dead centre are there in lathe. These two centres take up the thrust due to metal cutting and the entire load of the workpiece on small bearing surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "In which type of lathe centre, the hard tip is wear resistant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tipped centre",
            "b) revolving centre",
            "c) ordinary centre",
            "d) half centre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In tipped centre, the hard tip is wear resistant. Wear resistant means they are not easily affected by friction or any other damage"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Why lathe centres are made of very hard materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) to resist deflection",
            "b) to resist wear",
            "c) to resist deflection and wear both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lathe centres are made of very hard to resist these both things-deflection and wear. The dead centre is subjected to wear due to friction."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Which type of centre is particularly suitable for taper turning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ball centre",
            "b) female centre",
            "c) half centre",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ball centre is particularly suitable for taper turning as per the definition of the ball centre. It has minimum wear and strain."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "What is the included angle of centre for general purpose work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 45",
            "c) 60",
            "d) 75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The included angle is usually 60 for general purpose work. Also, the included angel for heavy work is 75."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of lathe centres?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ordinary centre",
            "b) tipped centre",
            "c) ball centre",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Generally, the shank of all the centres is machined to the Morse 0 to 6 tapers."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Options": [
            "13. Grooves cut along the diameter of the centre point provide for",
            "good gripping of the job and for getting the drive, in self-driving live centre.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:a\nExplanation: This is true. These lathe centers are made up of very hard materials as they have to resist entire load of the workpiece and thrust."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Which type of centre is used while facing the job without disturbing the setting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ball centre",
            "b) pipe centre",
            "c) half centre",
            "d) revolving centre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Ordinary centre is also known as common type centre."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "The centres take up_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) thrust due to metal cutting",
            "b) entire load of the work piece on small bearing surface",
            "c) thrust due to metal cutting and entire load of the work piece on small bearing surface both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Half centre is used while facing the job without disturbing the setting as per the classification of the lathe centres. Though it is termed as half centre, little less than half is relieved at the tip portion."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "A carbide or a hard alloy tip is brazed into an ordinary steel shank. For which type of centre, above sentence is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pipe centre",
            "b) half centre",
            "c) female centre",
            "d) tipped centre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The centres take up the thrust due to metal cutting and load on small bearing surface. So they are made of very hard materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "In which type of lathe centre, minimum wear and strain are obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pipe centre",
            "b) ball centre",
            "c) insert-type centre",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Above statement is true for the tipped centre as per the definition of the tipped centre. The hard tip is wear resistant in case of tipped centre. For tipped centres, a tip tool is there which is made of separate material clamped on separate body."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "In revolving centre, a high speed steel inserted centre is supported by_____ bearings housed in a body.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The dead centre is subjected to wear due to friction."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following centre is more economical?",
        "Options": [
            "a) insert-type centre",
            "b) pipe centre",
            "c) half centre",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ball centre,  minimum wear and strain are obtained. This ball centre is particularly suitable for taper turning."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of lathe centre?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pipe centre",
            "b) revolving centre",
            "c) insert-type centre",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Pipe centre is frictionless. It is used for supporting pipes shells and hollow end jobs."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to drive the work during turning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) catch plates",
            "b) carriers",
            "c) both catch plates and carriers",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lathe dogs term is also used for describing carriers. The carriers consist of a clamping screw."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "The work is clamped firmly by a set screw in the lathe_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) catch plates",
            "b) carriers",
            "c) both catch plates and carriers",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both catch plates and carriers are used to drive the work during turning. A projecting pin from the catch plate or carrier fits into the slot provided in either of them."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "The catch plates are_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) screwed",
            "b) bolted",
            "c) either screwed or bolted",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The work is clamped in the lathe carriers. It is done by a set of screw. A positive drive between the lathe spindle and workpiece is also imparted."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "The carrier may consists of_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) cast iron",
            "b) forged steel body",
            "c) clamping screw",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The catch plated are either screwed or bolted. A projecting pin of a single pin catch plate drives the straight end  or tail of a carrier attached to the work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "The tails of the carrier is meant to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) locate the work piece",
            "b) drive the work piece",
            "c) both locate the work piece and drive the work piece",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The catch plates are bolted to the nose of tailstock spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of catch plate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single pin catch plate",
            "b) double pin catch plate",
            "c) double slotted catch plate",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The carrier may consist of a cast iron or forged steel body and a clamping screw. To protect the finished surface from damages, a soft metal packing piece is used under this clamping screw."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "The bent tail type is used in conjunction with_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) a face plate",
            "b) a slotted catch plate",
            "c) a face plate or a slotted catch plate",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Generally, The carrier is available in a set of 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the projecting pin of a single pin catch plate drives the straight end or tail of a carrier attached to the work piece",
            "b) two pins of a double pin catch plate engage with the double tail or double slotted carrier",
            "c) two pins of a double pin catch plate provide non-uniform drive",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tail of the carriers are meant to locate and drive the work piece for turning. Two pins of a double catch plate engage with the double tail or double slotted carrier and provide uniform driver."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of carrier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) straight tail carrier",
            "b) double slotted carrier",
            "c) double tail carrier",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. To protect the finished surface from damages, a soft metal packing piece is used under the clamping screw."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Three jaw chuck is also known as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) universal chuck",
            "b) self-centering chuck",
            "c) universal or self-centering chuck",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Three jaw chuck is also known as universal or self centering chuck. The majority of the chucks have two sets of jaws for holding internal and external diameters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "A chuck is attached to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) lathe spindle",
            "b) lathe apron",
            "c) lathe tool post",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A chuck is attached to lathe spindle. This attachment is done with the help of bolts with the back plate. (as per the construction of the lathe.)"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Which type of work should be held in three jaw chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) perfectly round work",
            "b) work with equally spaced flats",
            "c) perfectly round work and work with equally spaced",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Back plate is screwed on the spindle nose. Accurate alignment of the chuck with the lathe axis is effected by spigotting."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Which of the following chuck is also known as hydraulic chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) combination chuck",
            "b) drill chuck",
            "c) none of the mentioned",
            "d) magnetic chuck"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Only perfectly round work or work with equally spaced flats, divisible by three should be held in a three jaw chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Which of the following chuck is also known as dog chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) four jaw chuck",
            "b) three jaw chuck",
            "c) two jaw chuck",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The answer should be none of mentioned. None of above is known as hydraulic chuck. Actually, air chuck is known as hydraulic chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": " In four jaw chuck, work can be turned within_____ mm accuracy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 22",
            "b) 2.2",
            "c) 0.022",
            "d) 0.0022"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dog chuck is also used for describing the four jaw chuck. Four jaw chuck is also known as independent chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "10.Which of the following is not true regarding four jaw chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Each jaw can be adjusted independently.",
            "b) Movement of jaw is irreversible.",
            "c) Movement of jaw is done by the help of square threaded screw.",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In four jaw chuck, work can be turned within 0.022 mm accuracy.As per the theory of four jaw chuck, this chuck also provides the facility of deliberately setting the work off-centre to produce eccentric workpiece."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the part of the four jaw chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) back plate",
            "b) shaft chuck key",
            "c) screw",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Four jaw chuck is independent chuck since each jaw can be adjusted independently."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "In four jaw chuck, a work piece can be set to run_____ by suitable adjustment of the jaws.",
        "Options": [
            "a) true",
            "b) eccentric",
            "c) true or eccentric",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Four jaw chuck is much more heavily constructed than self-centering chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "T bolts are used for_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) clamping irregular works",
            "b) assembling balance weights",
            "c) both clamping irregular works and assembling balance weights",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the sentences are true except the one which says that movement of jaw is irreversible. Actually, in this chuck, movement of jaw is reversible."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Generally, which type of work piece is hold in chucks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) of short length and small diameter",
            "b) of large length and small diameter",
            "c) of short length and large diameter",
            "d) of large length and large diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A chuck is one of the most important devices for holding and rotating a work piece in a lathe. Generally, workpiece of short length and large diameters are held in chucks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Which type of diameters does three jaw chuck hold?",
        "Options": [
            "a) internal diameter",
            "b) external diameter",
            "c) internal and external diameter both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above sentence is wrong.  The majority of the three jaw chucks have two sets of jaws."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of lathe chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) combination chuck",
            "b) magnetic chuck",
            "c) air chuck",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Three jaw chuck can hold both type of diameters : internal and external. Only perfect round work or work with equally spaced flats, divisile by three should be held in a 3 jaw chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Which type of job, does the scroll perform in three jaw chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) only clamps a component in place",
            "b) locates the component",
            "c) clamps a component in place and locates the component",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are  types of chucks. The all types of chucks are mentioned below.\n1. four jaw chuck\n2. three jaw chuck\n3. two jaw chuck\n4. combination chuck\n5. collet chuck\n6. magnetic chuck\n7. drill chuck\n8. hydraulically operated chuck\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of four jaw chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) body",
            "b) shaft chunk key",
            "c) pinion",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Scroll does both jobs. The scroll not only clamps a component in place but also locates the component.This is fundamentally a practice since any wear in the scroll and/or the jaw impairs the accuracy of location."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of three jaw chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) chuck key",
            "b) crown wheel",
            "c) back plate",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Three jaw chucks is irreversible."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "In combination chuck, jaws may be adjusted as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) independently",
            "b) together",
            "c) either independently or together",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Body and shaft chunk key are the parts of three jaw chuck but pinion is not the part of three jaw chuck. Pinion is the part of three jaw chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following pair is correct regarding to the arrangement of the jaw?",
        "Options": [
            "a) four jaw – independent",
            "b) three jaw – self centric",
            "c) two jaw chuck – independent",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are part of three jaw chuck. Chuck key, crown wheel and back plate are the important part of the three jaw chuck. In three jaw chuck, separate internal ans external jaws have to be used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding three jaw chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) if we rotate any one of three pinions, it may meshes with the teeth",
            "b) the scroll disc, which has a spiral groove cut on the bottom face meshes with the teeth on the jaws",
            "c) all these three jaws may be made to move simultaneously",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the chuck is designed with two jaws, it can be used as a turning mixture. Both jaws are adjustable and can be operted independently."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) jobs are held by operating the centering arrangement In combination type of chuck",
            "b) jaws may be specially machined to hold a particular type of job in two jaw chuck",
            "c) only one jaw may be operated concentric to the centre in two jaw chuck",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In combination chuck, both types of arrangements are possible. Combination chuck is normally a four jaw chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding two jaw concentric chuck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the feature related to construction of this type of chuck are similar to those three jaw and four jaw chuck",
            "b) both types of jaws are adjustable",
            "c) both types of jaws may not be operated independently",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are correct regarding the arrangement of the jaw. Both four jaw and two jaw chucks are independent chucks, while three jaw chuck is self centering chuck."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "How many machined faces do angle plates have?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angle plates are always used along with face plates and for its stability it is made up of iron.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following is provided on the faces of angle plates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) holes",
            "b) slots",
            "c) holes and slots both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Angle plates have two plates. Both of these plates are placed perpendicular to each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "In angle plates, clamping is used for______",
        "Options": [
            "a) elbow pipe",
            "b) angle plate",
            "c) both elbow pipe and angle plate",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Holes and slots both are provided on the faces of angle plates so that it may be clamped on a face plate and can hold the work piece on the other face."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for angle plates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) when eccentric jobs are bolted to the face plate, counter weight must be added",
            "b) in machining a flange of a pipe elbow, the surface which holds the work piece must be placed horizontal",
            "c) for balance weight, angle plates are used",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angle plates are used in conjunction with a face plate. It can be easily understood by looking at the working of the angle plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Face plates are used with_____ accessories.",
        "Options": [
            "a) clamps",
            "b) T- bolts",
            "c) stepped block",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Clamping is used for this both purposes. Angel plate is used in machining a flange of a pipe elbow."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "For holding work pieces, which cannot be conveniently between centers,  _____ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) three jaw chuck",
            "b) four jaw chuck",
            "c) face plates",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All sentences are true. These all are the mechanisms related to angel plates. Angel plates are used along with face plates when work can not be done by chucks or when we need higher accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for face plates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) a face plate consists of a circular disc bored out",
            "b) the work piece includes casting and jigs may not be clamped by using face plates",
            "c) face plates are used as an alternative option of chucks",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Face plates are used with all mentioned accessories. A face plate plate has radial plain and T slots for holding work by bolts and clamps."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Face plates has_____ for holding work by bolts and clamps.",
        "Options": [
            "a) radial plain",
            "b) slots of T type",
            "c) both radial plain and T slots",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Face plates are used for these purposes. The work piece include large flat, irregular shaped workpieces, casting, jigs and fixture may be firmly clamped to a face plate for various turning operations."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Faces of angle plates are_____ to each other.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) inclined",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The position of the bolts and clamps is very important in face plates, if a work piece is to be clamped effectively. Various types of face plates are used for proper clamping like face plates with elongated slots, face plates with elongated radial slots and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Work piece can be hold on a face plate by_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) bolts",
            "b) clamps",
            "c) both bolts and clamps",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the mentioned sentences are true except one which says that the work piece includes casting and jigs may not be clamped by using face plates. The work piece includes casting and jibs may be firmly clamped by using face plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the work piece must have their bores machined accurately",
            "b) the mandrels are to be located before the centres",
            "c) mandrels are used for turning concentric",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Mandrels are used for holding hollow work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Mandrels are driven by_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) catch plates",
            "b) carriers",
            "c) catch plates and carriers both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the sentences are true except one which says that the mandrel are to be located before the centres. The mandrels should  be located in between the centres."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Why gripping mandrels are made of high carbon steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) to avoid distortion",
            "b) to avoid wear",
            "c) both to avoid distortion and wear",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both are used to drive the mandrels. Catch plates are either screwed or bolted to the nose of the tailstock spindle while the carriers consist of a cast iron or forged steel body."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Less common but very often used method is_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel mandrel",
            "b) threaded cone mandrel",
            "c) both parallel mandrel and threaded cone mandrel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The diameters at the end are slightly smaller and flattened to provide effective gripping surface of the lathe dog set screw.."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "The mandrels are driven into the work by tapping by_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) copper hammers",
            "b) lead hammers",
            "c) copper hammer and lead hammer both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gripping mandrels are made of high carbon steel to avoid both distortion and wear. Along with this, the gripping power of this mandrels is not much."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the mandrels are used depending upon the specific requirements of the job.",
            "b) the gripping power of mandrels is very high",
            "c) effective gripping surface of the lathe dog set screw is done",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are several types of mandrels in use depending upon the specific requirements of the job. Less common but very often used is the parallel mandrel and the threaded cone mandrel."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of mandrels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plain mandrels",
            "b) stepped mandrels",
            "c) collar mandrels",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mandrels are driven into the work by tapping with copper and lead hammers or by an arbor press or by mandrel press.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which of the following mandrels are most commonly used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plain mandrels",
            "b) stepped mandrels",
            "c) collar mandrels",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All mentiones sentences are true except one which says that the gripping power of the mandrel is very high. The gripping power of the mandrels is not much."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "The difference in diameter is_____ mm per 100 mm length in case of the plain mandrels.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1to 2",
            "b) 4 to 5",
            "c) 8 to 10",
            "d) 10 to 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All of mentioned are the types of mandrels. Apart from these other types of mandrels are also there like expansion mandrel, gang mandrel and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Plain mandrel is suitable for_____ size of bore.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only one",
            "b) two",
            "c) more than two",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Turning a job on mandrels should be with light cuts."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "In plain mandrels, length varies from_____ mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 to 90",
            "b) 125 to 300",
            "c) 55 to 430",
            "d) 235 to 660"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The plain mandrels are most commonly used. It is also known as simple mandrel."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true in case of plain mandrel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the body of the mandrel is heavily tapered",
            "b) the taper is provided for proper gripping of the work piece",
            "c) the size of mandrel is indicated at the flat end portion of the mandrel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the mentioned sentences are true except the one which says that the body of mandrel is heavily tapered. Actually, its body is just slightly tapered."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Stepped mandrels are used for turning______",
        "Options": [
            "a) collars",
            "b) washers",
            "c) odd sized jobs",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stepped mandrels are used for collars, washers, odd sized jobs and so on. The stepped mandrel will have steps of different diameters to accommodate different workpieces. "
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about steeped mandrels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it can have steps of different diameters",
            "b) it can accommodate different work pieces having different sizes of holes",
            "c) removal of mandrel is necessary each time",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Removal of mandrel is not necessary each time. Sometimes, it can accommodate work piece without removing the mandrel."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which of the following mandrel is mostly used for work piece having internal threads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) stepped mandrel",
            "b) collar mandrel",
            "c) gang mandrel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In collar mandrel, mandrels are provided with solid collars for turning work pieces having holes of large diameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "In screwed mandrel, the threads_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) are left handed",
            "b) are right handed",
            "c) may be left or right handed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The construction of collar mandrel reduces its weight considerably and that’s the reason why it fits better than solid mandrel of equal size."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for screwed mandrel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the screw mandrel is threaded at one end with a collar",
            "b) the work piece are screwed on to the threaded portion against the collar for machining",
            "c) screw mandrels are used for turning the internal surfaces of screwed flanges, back plates of chucks etc",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Answer should be none of the mentioned. Screw mandrel is mostly used for work piece having internal threads."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "P mandrel consists of a solid one attached to one end and a sliding cone and adjusting nut on the other end. Identify P.",
        "Options": [
            "a) plain mandrel",
            "b) stepped mandrel",
            "c) cone mandrel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In screwed mandrel, the threads may be left or right handed. Screw mandrels are used for turning the external surfaces of screwed flanges, back plates of chucks etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the part of gang mandrel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fixed collar",
            "b) movable collar",
            "c) nut",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the mentioned sentences are true except the one which says that screw mandrels are used for turning the internal surfaces of screwed flanges, back plates of chucks etc. Actually, screw mandrels are used for turning the external surfaces of screwed flanges, back plates of chucks etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "In expansion mandrel, how many longitudinal slots are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is the property of cone mandrel. This type of mandrel is suitable for holding workpieces of different diameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "P mandrel is often provided with adapters or sleeves of different diameters to fit a wide variety of work piece bores. Identify P.",
        "Options": [
            "a) gang mandrel",
            "b) expansion mandrel",
            "c) collar mandrel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The cone should not be tightened too much over the work piece otherwise the outer surface the outer edge may get spoiled."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Expanding mandrels can be______ at one end.",
        "Options": [
            "a) plane",
            "b) threaded",
            "c) either plane or threaded",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All of the mentioned are the parts of the gang mandrel. A set of hollow workpieces are mounted on this mandrel and tightened with a nut. The friction between the sides of the work and collar drives the work without any slippage."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "P is lathe accessory used to give extra support for a long slender work pieces. Identify P.",
        "Options": [
            "a) steady rests",
            "b) tool post",
            "c) mandrels",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steady rests is lathe accessory used to give extra support for a long slender work pieces in addition to the centre support during turning."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Rests are used when support from_____ end cannot be given for drilling, reaming, tapping etc.",
        "Options": [
            "a) headstock",
            "b) tailstock",
            "c) apron",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rests are used when support from tailstock end cannot be given for drilling, reaming, tapping etc. These rests are fixed at some intermediate points to prevent bonding of work pieces due to their own weight."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "The jaws can be moved readily_____ by means of adjusting screws in fixed steady rest.",
        "Options": [
            "a) in",
            "b) out",
            "c) either in or out",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The jaws can be moved readily in or out by means of adjusting screws. The three jaws are adjusted on a trued cylindrical face of the work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "The rest are fixed to prevent the vibration set up due to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) own weight",
            "b) chattering forces",
            "c) own weight and chattering forces both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rest are fixed to prevent the vibration set up due to chattering forces. The use of this rest eliminates the chatter."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for rests?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rests are used when the length of the work piece is 10 to 15 times the diameters",
            "b) rests help in achieving greater accuracy in machining",
            "c) rests permit only light cuts",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All mentioned sentences are true except the one which says that the rests are permits only light cuts. Rests permit only heavy cuts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of steady rest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fixed steady rest",
            "b) follower steady rest",
            "c) both fixed steady rest and follower steady rest",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both are the types of steady rest. A fixed steady rest is fixed to the lathe bed while follower steady rest consists of a c like frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the parts of fixed rest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) adjustable pads",
            "b) locking screw",
            "c) bearing pads",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All above mentioned are the parts of fixed rest. Apart from these, base, bed clamp, hinge etc. are also the parts of fixed steady rest."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Fixed steady rest gives support at_____ fixed place only.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) more than two",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fixed steady rest is stationary because it is fixed to the lathe bed."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Fixed steady rest consists of a frame containing_____ adjustable pad.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fixed steady rest gives support at one fixed place only. A fixed steady rest can be clamped at any desired position on the lathe bed."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Options": [
            "11. The top of the frame is machined to suit the inside ways of the",
            "lathe bed in fixed steady rest.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fixed steady rest consists of a frame containing three adjustable pads. These pads are also known as jaws. "
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Which portion of the bed is hinged at the back in fixed steady rest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) top",
            "b) middle",
            "c) bottom",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The top portion of the bed is hinged at the back to permit the top to be lifted or assembled to the bottom half."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "In fixed steady rest, a fixed steady can be clamped_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel to lathe bed",
            "b) perpendicular to lathe bed",
            "c) at any desired position on the lathe bed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A fixed steady can be clamped at any desired position on the lathe bed. This is done with the help of base clamping screw."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "In fixed steady rests, these rests are fixed at some intermediate points to prevent bending of work pieces due to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) own weight",
            "b) chattering forces",
            "c) own weight and chattering forces both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: These rests are fixed at some intermediate points to prevent bending of work pieces due to their own weight. This rests help in achieving greater accuracy in machining and permit heavier cuts."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for fixed steady rest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the three pads or jaws are adjusted on a trued cylindrical face of the work piece",
            "b) a fixed steady can be clamped by the base clamping screw",
            "c) pads are also known as jaws",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The all above mentioned are true. Jaws can also be termed as pads and also a fixed steady rest can be clamped by base clamping screws."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as the travelling steady?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fixed steady rest",
            "b) follower steady rest",
            "c) fixed steady rest and follower steady rest both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Follower steady rest is also termed as travelling steady. Adjustable screw, bearing pads, frame, lock nut etc. are the main parts of this machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Follower steady rest consists of_____ like frame.",
        "Options": [
            "a) D",
            "b) C",
            "c) S",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Follower steady rest consists of ‘C’ like frame. These type of rest is used in finish turning operations or where the entire length of the workpiece is to be turned at a stretch, without disturbing the setting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "How many adjustable pads does follower steady rest has?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Follower steady rest has 2 adjustable pads. These pads are helpful for supporting the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "In follower steady rest, there is a pad which is located_____ the cutting tool.",
        "Options": [
            "a) in front of",
            "b) opposite to",
            "c) besides",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pad is located opposite to the cutting tool and the other pad bears the top of the workpiece to prevent from spinning up due to the thrust of the load. "
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Options": [
            "9. In follower steady rest, the work piece is machined slightly wider",
            "than the jaws.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The piece of work is machined slightly wider than jaws to provide bearing surface. For this, the machine surface is brought under the jaws and the tool is set slightly in advanced position than the jaws."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Which type feed is provided in follower steady rest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal",
            "b) cross",
            "c) both cross and longitudinal",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tool is fed longitudinally in follower steady rest and the jaws follow the tool giving support where cutting actually take place.."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for steady follower rest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is used in finish turning operation",
            "b) it is used where the entire length of the work piece is to be turned at a stretch, without disturbing the setting",
            "c) the support is discontinuous to the entire length of cutting",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All above sentences are true except the sentence which says that support is discontinuous to the entire length of cutting.The support is continuous to the entire length of cutting. "
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of the following tool material is not suitable for small diameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbon steel",
            "b) carbides",
            "c) carbon and carbides both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbides are not suitable for small diameters as these carbides has higher speeds and generally used in rapid stock removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following cutting material cannot be forged to shape easily?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbides",
            "b) ceramic",
            "c) stellites",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stellites cannot be forged to shape easily because they are very brittle in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the disadvantage of diamonds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) incompressible",
            "b) readily conducts heat",
            "c) rigid machine are required",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For ceramics, we need rigid machines. The other two mentioned disadvantages are true for diamond."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "High speed steel has an excessive wear on______",
        "Options": [
            "a) castings",
            "b) hard materials",
            "c) casting and hard materials both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It has excessive wear on casting and hard materials and that’s why can only perform slow and medium cutting speeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following has poor shock resistant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbides",
            "b) diamonds",
            "c) ceramics",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ceramic has poor shock resistant. Apart from this,  it has high wear resistance and again has very high stock removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "In which tool material, rigid machines are required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ceramics",
            "b) carbon steel",
            "c) diamonds",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ceramics are used for this purpose. They are not suitable for intermittent cut and even for small diameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Machine tools must be tough enough to withstand_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) shock",
            "b) vibration",
            "c) both shock and vibration",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Machine tools must be tough enough to withstand these both in order to provide stability against downward pressure and to perform the job more accurately."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Carbides are used in_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) rapid stock removal",
            "b) higher speeds",
            "c) rapid stock removal and higher speed both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Carbides are used for these both reasons. But they are not used for comparatively small jobs."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "“Light finishing cuts in expensive forming tools”- this quality is applicable to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbides",
            "b) ceramics",
            "c) stellites",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The answer should be none of mentioned. This is the quality of carbon steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Which of the following is easy to grind and generally used for intermittent cut?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbides",
            "b) diamond",
            "c) high speed steel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: High speed steel has some advanced quality and so it is very accurate even on small diameters. So it is easy to grind high speed steel. Again, this high speed steel is generally used for intermittent cut."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "“High compressive strength with negative rake” – this is applicable to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbides",
            "b) diamonds",
            "c) carbon steel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the quality of carbides. That’s why they are not suitable for very small diameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following tool material has excessive wear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbon steel",
            "b) high speed steel",
            "c) carbon steel and high speed steel both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These both materials have excessive wear. They have excessive wear on castings and hard materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the use of diamond?",
        "Options": [
            "a) good for finishing work",
            "b) suitable for cutting hard metals",
            "c) rapid stock removal",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Stellites is good for non metal cutting application."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "For general purpose, which type of cutting tool is used in lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single point",
            "b) multi point",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diamond is not used for rapid stock removal. For rapid stock removal, carbides and ceramics are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "For specific purpose, which type of cutting tool is used in lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single point",
            "b) multi point",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For general purpose, single point cutting tool is used. Like both shaper and planer are single point cutting tool that only cut in straight line."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of cutting tool material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbon steel",
            "b) stellites",
            "c) diamond",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For specific purpose, multi point cutting tool is used. Milling and drilling are generally multi point cutting tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Which of the following is very brittle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) stellites",
            "b) diamond",
            "c) both diamond and stellites",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Ceramics are not suitable for intermittent cut."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following can machine the metals effectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diamonds",
            "b) ceramics",
            "c) both diamonds and ceramics",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The answer should be none of the mentioned. All are the types of cutting tool material."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Lathe cutting tool can be classified according to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) manufacturing of tool",
            "b) method of holding tool",
            "c) method of using tool",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cutting tool can be classified according to all mentioned parameters. Generally in lathe we use single point cutting tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Which of the following cutting tool can have single roller?",
        "Options": [
            "a) boring tool",
            "b) knurling tool",
            "c) both boring tool and knurling tool",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both boring tool and knurling tool can have single roller. Generally, boring tool is used to enlarge the hole. Knurling is used when we need a pattern of straight, cross and angular lines cutting each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Lathe cutting tool can be classified as right hand and left hand according to_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) method of using the tool",
            "b) method of holding the tool",
            "c) method of applying feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lathe cutting tool can be classified as right hand and left hand according to method of applying feed. Here, feed is the distance the tool advances for each revolution of the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of left hand type cutting tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) roughing tool",
            "b) facing tool",
            "c) finishing tool",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are the types of left hand cutting tool. Facing, roughing and finishing are one kind of turning operations often carried out on lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "According to the method of using the tool, lathe cutting tool can be classified as_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) turning",
            "b) grooving",
            "c) forming",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to the method of using the tool, lathe cutting tool can be classified as turning, grooving, forming, chamfering, internal thread cutting, parting-off and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of classification as per the method of manufacturing the tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tipped tool, which is brazed to the carbon steel shank",
            "b) tipped tool, which is fastened mechanically to the carbon steel shank",
            "c) grooving",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Here, grooving is not the type of classification according to the method of manufacturing the tool. Grooving is the type of classification according to the method of using the tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "“Tool bit inserted in the (tool) holder and solid tool” – is included in the classification according to the_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) method of using tool",
            "b) method of manufacturing tool",
            "c) method of applying feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All options are incorrect. Answer should be none of mentioned. It is suitable with the classification of cutting tool as per the method of holding the tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "‘Internal thread cutting’- is suitable with the classification of cutting tool according to the______",
        "Options": [
            "a) method of using the tool",
            "b) method of holding the tool",
            "c) method of manufacturing the tool",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the classification of cutting tool. Apart from internal thread cutting, boring, facing, forming etc. are also included in this category. "
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "‘Round nose’ – is suitable with the classification of cutting tool according to the______",
        "Options": [
            "a) method of holding tool",
            "b) method of holding tool",
            "c) method of the applying feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It can be easily understood by looking at the classification of cutting tool. Apart from round nose, right hand tool and left hand tool are also included in this category."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "‘Parting-off’ – is suitable with the classification of cutting tool according to the______",
        "Options": [
            "a) method of manufacturing the tool",
            "b) method of holding the tool",
            "c) method of using the tool",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ‘Parting-off’ – is suitable with the classification of cutting tool according to the method of using the tool. This parting uses a blade like cutting tool into workpiece in order to cut the metal at the speed of spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "For lathe operations, work piece can be hold _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) between centres",
            "b) on mandrel",
            "c) either between centres or on mandrel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Work piece can be hold either between centers or on mandrel. Mandrels are used for holding hollow workpieces for turning concentric to the bore."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to drive the work piece?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carriers",
            "b) catch plates",
            "c) both carriers and catch plates",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Work piece can be driven by using both of these. Catch plates are either screwed or bolted to the nose of the tailstock spindle while the carriers consists of a cast iron or forged steel body."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Grinding can be performed by______",
        "Options": [
            "a) using faceplates or angle plates",
            "b) using chucks",
            "c) special attachments",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be seen from the working of lathe operations. Several types of chucks are there like 4 jaw chuck, 3 jaw chuck and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Taper boring and the under boring can be performed by______",
        "Options": [
            "a) centers",
            "b) face plates or angle plates",
            "c) special attachments",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Knurling can be done by a chuck on holding work piece between centres."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Milling can be performed by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) centres",
            "b) face plates or angel plates",
            "c) chucks",
            "d) special attachments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grinding can be done by special attachments. Grinding is a type of machining using an abrasive type of wheel as the cutting tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Spinning can be done by_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) centres",
            "b) face plates or angle plates",
            "c) special attachments",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Both types of plates can be used for this purpose. A face plate consists of a circular disk bored out and threaded to sit the nose of the lathe spindle while angel plate is a cast iron plate having two faces machined to make them absolutely at right angles to each other. "
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Reaming and counter boring can be performed by______",
        "Options": [
            "a) centres",
            "b) face plates and angle plates",
            "c) special attachments",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Milling can be performed by special attachments. Milling machine is a machine tool that removes metal as the work is fed against a rotating multipoint cutter."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "A taper may be defined as a uniform gradual_____ along the length of the job.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase",
            "b) decrease",
            "c) increase or decrease",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A taper may be defined as a uniform gradual increase or decrease along the length of the job.  Taper turning can be measured by from tool method, tailstock offset method, compound slide method and so on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "In a lathe, taper turning means to produce a_____ surface by gradually decreasing the value of diameter from a cylindrical work piece.",
        "Options": [
            "a) conical surface",
            "b) flat surface",
            "c) both conical and flat surface",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The taper is measured in terms of diameter along the length of job."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for taper turning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) taper turning is one type of lathe operation",
            "b) the amount of taper is specified by the ratio of its length to the difference in the diameter of the taper",
            "c) amount of taper is designated by the letter K",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Taper turning means to produce a conical surface by gradually decreasing the value of diameter from a cylindrical work  piece lathe. Two types of tapers are there: internal and external taper."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "The SI unit of taper is_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) meter",
            "b) centimeter",
            "c) millimeter",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the sentences are true except the sentence which says that the amount of taper is specified by the ratio of its length to the difference in the diameter of the taper. The amount of taper is specified by the ratio of difference in the diameters of the taper to its length."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the right formula for taper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) K= (D-d) / L",
            "b) K= L / (D-d)",
            "c) K= D/ L",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily understood by the definition of taper. For taper or conicity feed is provided. Two types of feeds are there: manual feed and power feed."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Find the value of K. D= 90 mm, d=80 mm, L=1cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 100",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Taper is ratio of same quantity. It is unitless."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Find the value of d. K=1/10, L= 10 cm, D=65 mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 mm",
            "b) 55 cm",
            "c) 75 mm",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Half taper angle is also known as angle of taper. "
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the method of taper turning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) compound rest method",
            "b) tailstock offset method",
            "c) attachment method",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are methods of taper turning.By using compound rest method and and attachment method, both internal and external taper can be turned while tailstock offset method is used only for external tapers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "From tool method is generally used for_____ production for producing_____ length of taper.",
        "Options": [
            "a) mass, small",
            "b) mass, long",
            "c) little, small",
            "d) little, long"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. From tool method is used when accuracy is not the major criterion.The form tool should be set at right angels to the axis of the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "In compound slide method, which of the following is swiveled?",
        "Options": [
            "a) top slide",
            "b) swivel base",
            "c) apron",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This method is used for mass production for producing small length of taper."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "In compound slide method, one part of compound rest is swiveled to_____ the included angle of the taper.",
        "Options": [
            "a) the same as",
            "b) half",
            "c) double",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Tailstock method is not suitable for producing steep tapers."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "In compound rest method, the amount of taper for setting the angle is calculated from this formula, tan of angle of taper =_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) (D-d) / L",
            "b) (D-d) / 2L",
            "c) (D-d) / 4L",
            "d)  none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Lengthy taper can be produced by this method.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which type of tapers can be produced by using compound rest method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) internal",
            "b) external",
            "c) both internal and external",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Top slide is swiveled in this method. It is swiveled to half the included angel of the taper."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for compound slide method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) threads, which are there on taper portion cannot be produced",
            "b) steep taper cannot be produced",
            "c) taper length is limited to the movement of the top slide",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In compound slide method, one part of compound rest is swiveled (at half the included angle of the taper). We can easily set this compound slide."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "In attachment method, the bar having graduations in degree is set at the_____ with the lathe axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 degree",
            "b) 90 degree",
            "c) any desired angle",
            "d) 180 degree"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: (D-d) / 4L – this is the formula for the tan of the angel of taper. Taper is the shape in which the diameter of the both ends are different. "
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "In compound slide method, taper length is limited to the movement of_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) apron",
            "b) swivel base",
            "c) top slide",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both internal and external taper can be produced by using compound slide method. But there is one disadvantage. We can only give hand feed so we can’t expect a high accurate and mass work."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "The taper can be turned up to maximum setting angle of_____ for both outside and inside tapers with taper attachment and automatic feed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 to 6 degree",
            "b) 1 to 2 degree",
            "c) 10 to 12 degree",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All mentioned sentences are true except the sentence which says that steep taper can’t produced by this method. Steep taper can be produced by this method."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for attachment method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lengthy tapers can be produced",
            "b) the alignment of the lathe center is disturbed",
            "c) power feed can be given",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bar is set at any desired angle with the lathe axis. The principle of turning taper by attachment is to guide the tool in a straight path set an angel to the axis of rotation of the work piece, while the work is being revolved between centers or by a chuck aligned to the lathe axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "In tailstock offset method, the job is held at an angle and the tool moves______ to the axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) at 45 degree",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tool moves parallel to the axis in this method. the body of the tailstock is shifted on its base to an amount corresponding to the angle of taper."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "In tailstock method, the angle at which the axis of rotation of the job is shifted is equal to______ the angle of taper.",
        "Options": [
            "a) half",
            "b) double",
            "c) triple",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is angle is equal to half the angle of taper. This taper can be turned between centers only."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "In tailstock method, body of the tailstock is made to slide on its base_____ from the operation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) towards",
            "b) away",
            "c) either towards or away",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In tailstock method, body of the tailstock is made to slide on its base either away or towards from the operation. This operation is done with the help of setover screw.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Which type of taper is generally turned in tailstock method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) internal",
            "b) external",
            "c) both internal and external",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The form tool should be at right angle to the axis of the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for tailstock method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the body of tailstock is shifted on its base to an amount corresponding to the angle of taper",
            "b) the movement of tailstock is made by a setover screw",
            "c) accurate setting of the offset is easy",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only external taper can be turned in this method. Generally for internal threads this method is not used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for tailstock method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the taper can be turned between centres only",
            "b) duplicate tapers can be produced",
            "c) the alignment of the lathe centres will be disturbed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All the mentioned sentences are true except one which says that accurate setting of the offset is easy. Actually, accurate setting of the offset is difficult in this method."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the benefit of tailstock method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) power feed can be given",
            "b) good surface finish can be obtained",
            "c) maximum length of the taper can be produced",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the above sentences are true. These all sentences are related with tailstock method  in which the maximum length of the taper can be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "The taper turning attachment consists essentially of a frame which is attached to the_____ end of the lathe bed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) front",
            "b) rear",
            "c) both front and rear",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all are the benefits of the tailstock method. Apart from these benefits, we have some other benefits too like external threads on taper portion can be produced, duplicate tapers can be produced and so on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "In attachment method, cross-slide must be made_____ the lead screw.",
        "Options": [
            "a) fixed with",
            "b) free from",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the disadvantage of this method. Apart from it, it has other big disadvantage that only external taper can be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Which type of tapers can be produced by attachment method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) internal",
            "b) external",
            "c) both internal and external",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The taper turning attachment consists essentially of a frame which is attached to the rear end of the lathe bed. This attachment is provided only on a few modern lathes."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "In attachment method, the angle of swiveling the guide bar can be determined from this equation, tan of angle =______",
        "Options": [
            "a) (D-d) / L",
            "b) (D-d) / 2L",
            "c) (D-d) / 4L",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the biggest disadvantage of this method. Also, threads on taper portion cannot be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "The lead screw obtains_____ motion from the working spindle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) rotary",
            "b) transmitting",
            "c) both rotary and transmitting",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily understood by looking at the definition of the threading. The tool post holds the tool or tools meant for the operation to be performed on the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "The split is mounted in the_____ of the carriage.",
        "Options": [
            "a) saddle",
            "b) apron",
            "c) top slide",
            "d) cross slide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lead screw obtains rotary motion from the working spindle. The lead screw drives the tool post axially against the workpiece to produce a helical groove."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "In thread cutting, which type of feed motion is possible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) engaging",
            "b) disengaging",
            "c) either engaging or disengaging",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rotary motion is converted into feed motion. The ledscrew has a trapezoidal thread and obtains this rotary motion which converts into feed motion by split."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "In thread cutting, the _____ feeds should be equal to the pitch of the thread, which is to be cut per revolution of the work piece.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cross feed",
            "b) longitudinal feed",
            "c) angular feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the construction of the carriage. The apron is fastened to the saddle and hangs over the front of the bed."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "In thread cutting, which of the following receives traversing motion from the lead screw of the lathe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) apron",
            "b) top slide",
            "c) cross slide",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both types of feed motion is possible in thread cutting. In order to perform these feed motions split nut’s movement is required."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "In thread cutting, definite ratio is calculated between the_____ feed and rotation of the_____ spindle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal, headstock",
            "b) cross, headstock",
            "c) cross, tailstock",
            "d) longitudinal, tailstock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the definition of the longitudinal feeds. Again here the feed is the distance the tool advances for each revolution of work."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for thread cutting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tool post is driven by lead screw axially against the work piece",
            "b) the lead screw has a trapezoidal thread",
            "c) the relative type of speeds of  rotation of the work and the lead screw can result in the cutting of a screw of the desired pitch",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Saddle receives traversing motion from the lead screw of the lathe, This leadscrew has a definite pitch.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "In thread chasing dial, the half nut is_____ when any live on the dial coincides with a reference live already set.",
        "Options": [
            "a) opened",
            "b) closed",
            "c) partially opened and partially closed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The definite ratio is calculated between the longitudinal type of feed and the rotation of the headstock spindle. This ratio should be found out so that the relative speeds of rotation of the work and the leadscrew will result in the cutting of a screw of the desired pitch."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "In thread chasing dial, half nut is closed when any numbered live coincides with reference live for_____ thread.",
        "Options": [
            "a) even",
            "b) odd",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the sentences are true. These all mentioned sentences are the related with the working of the thread cutting which can be carried on a lathe to obtain standard forms and properties of screw threads by using appropriate tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "The chasing dial is mounted on the right end of the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) tool post",
            "b) apron",
            "c) head stock",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At this condition, the half nut is closed to avoid collision. Thread chasing dial is a special attachment used in cutting threads."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "In chasing dial, dial rotate as long as the half nut is_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) engaged",
            "b) not engaged",
            "c) either engaged or not engaged",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In thread chasing dial, half nut is closed when any numbered live coincides with reference live for odd thread. The dial indicates when to close the split nut."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "For feed motion, split nut has to be_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) always closed",
            "b) always opened",
            "c) either opened or closed (depend upon motion)",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chasing dial is mounted on the right end of the apron. This chasing dial is generally used to pick up the thread. "
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "The gear connections on a lathe______",
        "Options": [
            "a) always compound",
            "b) always simple",
            "c) may be simple or compound",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. The intermediate gear has no effect on the ratio between the driver and the driven, but merely acts as a connection between the two and serves to keep the rotation of the driver and driven in the same direction.\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "The gear on the stud shaft acts as a _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) driver",
            "b) driven",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gear connection on a lathe may be simple or compound depends upon the requirement. It is versatile."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as Norton gearbox?",
        "Options": [
            "a) simple gear train",
            "b) compound gear train",
            "c) quick change type of gearbox",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gear on the stud shaft act as a driver. It can be considered as spindle gear as usually it runs at the same spindle speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "In Norton gearbox, gear changing is effected by the movement of_____ levers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) three",
            "d) four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Quick change type of gearbox is also known as Norton gearbox. It covers all the ratio of screw cutting and feed rate likely to be wanted."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Teeth on driven gear / teeth on driver gear =_______ T.P.I on lead screw=a, T.P.I. on work piece=b.",
        "Options": [
            "a) a/b",
            "b) b/a",
            "c) a*b",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gear changing is affected by the movements of two levers as well as a sliding gear. This eliminates the need to remove and change the gears as in the standard change gearbox."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Driver gear/driven gear =______ pitch of work piece threads=a, pitch of lead screw =b.",
        "Options": [
            "a) a/b",
            "b) b/a",
            "c) a*b",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: (b/a) – This is the suitable ratio for threads where T.P.I on lead screw=a, T.P.I. on work piece=b. If the units of workpiece and leadscrew threads are different, in that case the gears are calculated as follows: 1 inch = 25.4 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Lead screw pitch=6mm, work piece pitch=1mm. Find change gears.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 1/6",
            "c) 3",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the suitable ratio. In British it will be equal to (a/b)*(5/127). "
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Change gear=2, lead screw pitch = 8. Find work piece pitch.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 16",
            "c) 2",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Change gear=work piece pitch/lead screw pitch. From this formula, we can easily get 1/6 as a answer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "In a compound train, the stud carriers______ gears.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Change gear=work piece pitch/lead screw pitch. So, work piece pitch = change gear*lead screw pitch\n                     = 2*8\n                     = 16\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "______ is the speed at which the metal is removed by the tool from the work piece.",
        "Options": [
            "a) feed",
            "b) cutting speed",
            "c) depth of cut",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It can be easily understood by looking at the definition of the cutting speed. Cutting speed is a peripheral speed of the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents the formula for cutting speed? cs =cutting speed, D= diameter of work, N= rpm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cs = (3.14*D*N)",
            "b) cs = (D*N)",
            "c) cs = (3.14*D)/N",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cs = (3.14*D*N) – This is the formula for finding the cutting speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following represent the unit of cutting speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) meter*minute",
            "b) meter*meter*minute",
            "c) meter / minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In cutting speed’s formula, d-diameter expressed in meter and n is rpm – revolution per minute. By putting this units in cutting speed’s formula, we can easily obtain its unit as meter/minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "_____ is the distance the tool advances for each revolution of the work.",
        "Options": [
            "a) feed",
            "b) depth of cut",
            "c) metal removal rate",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The feed of a cutting tool in a lathe work is the distance the tool advances for each revolution of the work. Increased feed reduces the cutting time."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the unit of the feed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm / minute",
            "b) mm / revolution",
            "c) mm * minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mm / revolution is the right unit for feed. In British system it is expressed in inches per revolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The depth of cut is the_____ distance measured from the machined surface to the surface of the work piece, which is uncut.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) at 45 degree",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the perpendicular distance measured from the machined surface to the surface of the work piece, which is uncut. Other factors remaining constant, the depth of cut varies inversely as the cutting speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents the formula for the depth of cut? d1=diameter of work surface before machining and d2=diameter of the machined surface",
        "Options": [
            "a) d1+d2",
            "b) d1-d2",
            "c) (d1+d2)/2",
            "d) (d1-d2)/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: (D1-d2) – this is the formula for depth of cut. Here both d1 and d2 are diameters and expressed in mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents the unit of metal removal rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm/revolution",
            "b) mm*mm/revolution",
            "c) mm*mm*mm/revolution",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: (a*b*c)/d – This is the right formula for metal removal rate. Here a is expressed in mm/minute, b is expressed in mm, c is expressed in mm/revolution and d is simply revolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents the unit for machining time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm / minute",
            "b) minute / revolution",
            "c) minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mm*mm*mm / revolution is the right unit for the metal removal rate. If we put the units of cutting speed, depth of cut and feed in formula we can easily get this result."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents the formula for the machining time? s=feed of the job per revolution, l=length of the job, n=rpm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) l / (s*n)",
            "b) (s*n) / l",
            "c) (l*s) / n",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Machining time is simply a time so its unit must be matched with time’s unit. Minute is the right unit for machining time."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "For general purposes, ratio of the depth of cut to the feed varies from_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10:1",
            "b) 1:10",
            "c) 100:1",
            "d) 1:100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Length of the job / (feed of the job per revolution*rpm) is the right for machining time. Also we can cross check the formula. Put the unit of each quantity and check in which formula we can get unit as a time’s unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of the following is included in basic machine tools?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lathe machine",
            "b) production milling machine",
            "c) production drilling machine",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the definition of basic type of machine tools, lathe is basic machine tool while production milling machine and production drilling machines are special purpose drilling machines."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Which type of machine tool is used for mass production of essentially small parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) general purpose",
            "b) special purpose",
            "c) automatic screw cutting",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The automatic type of screw cutting is used for this purpose. The automatic screw cutting is used because of its high accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the following does all the work of lathe machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) turning centre of CNC type",
            "b) machining centre of CNC type",
            "c) turning centre of CNC type and machining centre of CNC type both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This type of turning centre does most of jobs of lathe. Lathe is a basic machine used for producing cylindrical machine. It is considered as father of machine tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "CNC machining centre does all the work_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) milling machine",
            "b) drilling machine",
            "c) both milling and drilling machine",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CNC machining centre perform almost all jobs of milling and drilling machines. Drilling machine is used to produce holes and milling machines remove metal as the work is fed against a rotating multipoint cutter."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of lathe machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) capstan",
            "b) turret",
            "c) both capstan and turret",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These both are categorized under the types of lathe machine. Turret and capstan lathe are generally used for the production of duplicate parts"
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "DNC stands for_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) digital numerical control",
            "b) direct numerical control",
            "c) double numerical control",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the history of machine tools, Egyptians were the first, who used that. They used the cylinder."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Machine tools can be classified as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) geometric shape of the work piece",
            "b) number of the work piece",
            "c) function of the machine",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNC is the abstract form of direct numerical control."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Options": [
            "12. The demand of instruments or parts, which are used for",
            "purpose of measurements are more in NC machine tool.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Machine tools are only economical, when it is used for producing small number of pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Point consists of a_____ center.",
        "Options": [
            "a) dead",
            "b) live",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Point consists of a dead center. Dead center is edge which is sharp situated at the extreme tip of the drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "The cone-shaped end, which does the cutting is the_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) shank",
            "b) point",
            "c) tang",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the definition of point. This part performs the drilling work. Point is the very important for the drilling operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which of the following does the point consist?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lips",
            "b) cutting edges",
            "c) heel",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The point consists of all these things. Cutting edges of drill are known as lips. Heel is a portion of this point back from the cutting edge."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the driving end of the drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tang",
            "b) flute",
            "c) shank",
            "d) land"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shank is the driving end of the drill. This shank is clamped in the spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of shank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) taper shank",
            "b) straight shank",
            "c) taper shank and straight shank both",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both taper shank and straight shank are the types of it. Straight shank drill uses a chuck while taper shank uses self holding taps."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Taper shank is used for______ diameter drills.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) large",
            "c) both large and small",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For large diameter, taper shank is used. Self holding taps of this shank fits easily into the drill spindle and can perform the job easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of a body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) land",
            "b) margin",
            "c) flute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Body clearance is a part which is reduced with a purpose to cut down the friction between the drill and the wall of the hole. "
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "______ are the spiral grooves which run to the length of the drill.",
        "Options": [
            "a) tangs",
            "b) flutes",
            "c) shanks",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Tang fits into the slot of the drilling machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "The portion between the point and the shank is called______",
        "Options": [
            "a) body",
            "b) drill",
            "c) both body and drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are parts of body. Land and margin are synonyms. Apart from these, body clearance is also the part of body."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Table top drilling machine can be categorized as_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) general purpose drilling machine",
            "b) specific purpose drilling machine",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Table top drilling machine can be categorized as general purpose drilling machine as it is not used for any specific application."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which type of feed can be given in table top drilling machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) manual",
            "b) power",
            "c) both manual and power feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Manual feed is given in this machine. We don’t deal with very heavy jobs in table top drilling machine so manual feed can perform job sufficiently."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "In table top drilling machine, feed can be operated by_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) gear mechanism",
            "b) lever",
            "c) spindle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. Power produced is comparatively low because manual feed is given to this machine, not powered feed."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Generally, table top drilling machine can produce diameters up to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 mm",
            "b) 10 mm",
            "c) 100 mm",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The feed can be operated by lever in this machine. This lever can be operated manually to provide feed."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Table top drilling machine is generally______ in terms of height.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) big",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It can produce diameter up to 10 mm. As it is operated by manual feed, its power production is low so it is not used for producing large diameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "In table top drilling machine, belt-pulley system operates______",
        "Options": [
            "a) lever",
            "b) spindle",
            "c) both lever and spindle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be mounted or clamped on the table to accommodate with job."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for table top drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is used in only small jobs",
            "b) it is used for mass production",
            "c) odd shape jobs are not machined",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Table tap drilling machine is comparatively small in terms of height. It is hardly 1 to 3 feet long in height."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Distance between the table and drill is_____ in pillar drill machine as compare to table top drill machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) high",
            "c) same",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distance between the table and drill is more in pillar drill machine. Pillar drill uses a column and base along with drill making a sturdy as well as safe place to drill materials like wood and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for pillar drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is an extension of table top drill machine",
            "b) it is very strong",
            "c) it is not rigid",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All mentioned sentences are true except one which says that it is very strong. This type of machine is not very tough or strong."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which type of motion is possible for table in pillar drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) only swivel",
            "b) only upward and downward",
            "c) all swivel, upward and downward",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These all motions of table is possible in pillar drill machine in order to accommodate with job. "
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "The pillar drill machine can perform maximum______ mm of diameter job.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 100",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally, this machine cannot perform more than 20 mm diameter job. It is used for job below 20 mm diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "What is the maximum power that we can expect in pillar drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 Kw",
            "b) 1.1 Kw",
            "c) 5.5 Kw",
            "d) 11.1 Kw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. This machine has a long tubular column."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "The pillar drill machine can perform______ work.",
        "Options": [
            "a) light",
            "b) heavy",
            "c) both light and heavy",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this machine chances of vibrations are there as the column job is not very rigid."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for pillar drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is taller",
            "b) it can be mounted or fitted on ground or any other foundation",
            "c) for the production of one or two pieces of light work, this can be used",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the design, mechanism and performance, maximum 1.1 Kw power can be expected."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for pillar drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it looks like a pillar",
            "b) the table is movable",
            "c) it is not used for mass production",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This machine is ordinary machine, not made for specific purpose or special task and generally used only for light work."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which type of work can be performed in column drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) different job of material",
            "b) different diameter of drill",
            "c) different depth of drill",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all can be performed in column drill machine. That’s why it is commonly used in all industry. Its common machine and can’t used for heavy application."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for column drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is very light",
            "b) it is quite big in size",
            "c) different types of works can be done in this machine",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All sentences are true except the one which says that it is very light. In fact, it is very rigid and ragged machine"
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for column drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is strong machine structure",
            "b) it is very powerful machine",
            "c) it doesn’t allow high speed drilling",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Its production rate is comparatively low but it can perform the operation quite nicely and often used in industry."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for column drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) accuracy is less",
            "b) it is common type of drill machine used in industry",
            "c) it is very rigid",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All the sentences are true except the one which says that it doesn’t allow high speed drilling. This machine allows high speed drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Which type of gear box does column drill machine possess?",
        "Options": [
            "a) speed gear box",
            "b) feed gear box",
            "c) both speed gear box and feed gear box",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the sentences are true except the one which says that accuracy is less in column drill machine. Accuracy is comparatively high in this type of machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "To enable the spindle speed, one can vary_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) speed of spindle",
            "b) feed",
            "c) both speed of spindle and feed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both type of gear boxes are there in this machine. Now a days column drill machine are also available with hydraulic feed and multi spindle head."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "In which of the following machine, automatic feed is possible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) table top drill",
            "b) column drill",
            "c) pillar drill",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the construction of this machine. Drilling head is a heavy and most important part of the drilling machine where lever and other components are attached."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Options": [
            "12. Very odd types and heavy types jobs cannot be mounted and",
            "machined in column drill.",
            "a) true",
            "b) false"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. It can’t be used for mass production. It can be only used for small production as it is very rigid and intended only for some specific purposes. The rate at which produce the output is quite low."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "The rigidness of radial drill machine is______ column drill machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than",
            "b) same as",
            "c) more than",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Radial drills can make large diameter of holes so its rigidness should be more column drill machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Thickness of valve in the radial machine is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) large",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Valve thickness is quite large in this machine as it has to drill large diameter of holes."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Which type of movement is possible in case of radial arm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) only swivel",
            "b) only up and down",
            "c) all up, down and swivel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the construction of this machine. On this radial arm, the spindle head is mounted."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The movement of radial arm is______",
        "Options": [
            "a) manual",
            "b) powered",
            "c) either manual or powered",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only up and down movement is possible in this case. Generally, horizontal movement is not possible in radial arm."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following holds the drill spindle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) radial arm",
            "b) tubular column",
            "c) drilling head",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both movements are possible. But at the time when we have to deal with heavy and large workpieces the powered movement is more preferable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "The drilling head can move_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) inward and outward",
            "b) up and down",
            "c) all inward and outward and up and down",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Drilling head holds the drill spindle. There is a motor which is mounted on the spindle head rotates this spindle. "
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for radial drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it can work with jobs, which are odd shaped",
            "b) the tubular column is very thick and has small diameters",
            "c) drill is mounted on drilling spindle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These all types of motions are possible in this case. The drilling head is mounted on the radial arm."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for radial drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling spindle is subjected to rotation",
            "b) the entire drilling head is mounted on radial arm",
            "c) the gap between the drill and job is known as stroke length",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tubular is thick but it has large diameter not small."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "In radial arm, spindle may be_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical",
            "b) swiveling",
            "c) swiveling and tilting",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All sentences are true. There is a one thing that we should know about radial drilling machine is that we can make multiple holes in one setting of work. This is the advantage of the radial drilling machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which of the following machine is portable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hand drill",
            "b) none of mentioned",
            "c) pillar drill",
            "d) column drill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pillar drill and column drill are heavy enough to carry. Hand drill can be driven by hand."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Size of hand drill is relatively ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) medium",
            "c) large",
            "d) very large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Size of hand drill is relatively small. It is so small that man can hold it in his hand."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "In hand drill, force on the spindle is_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) less",
            "b) more",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, force on the spindle is less in this machine as this machine has to be carried by hand-manually. So smaller the force, more easier it to carry in hand. "
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "If you want to make a hole in a switch board, then you will use______",
        "Options": [
            "a) table top drill machine",
            "b) pillar drill machine",
            "c) hand drill machine",
            "d) column drill machine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hand drill is such a small that it can be hold by hand and for that it should be flexible for normal use. For that, generally we provide aerator system for the rotation of the spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "In which of the following drill machine, number of drills are used simultaneously?",
        "Options": [
            "a) table top drill machine",
            "b) pillar drill machine",
            "c) hand drill machine",
            "d) gang drill machine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hand drill machine is used for this purpose because it is portable. We can’t move switch board to the machine. Switch board is fixed. So, in order to perform drilling operation in switch board we need a portable device and for that purpose we use hand dril."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Which type of drilling can be done in gang drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) progressive",
            "b) parallel",
            "c) both progressive and parallel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gang drill is used for this purpose. As the name suggest, gang drill is used for gang production means for large production and for that it uses number of drills simultaneously."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Gang drill is used for______",
        "Options": [
            "a) large-batch production",
            "b) small production",
            "c) relatively low production",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both types of drills can be performed in this machine as number of drills can be used simultaneously."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "In which of the following, accuracy is more?",
        "Options": [
            "a) table top drill",
            "b) hand drill",
            "c) pillar drill",
            "d) gang drill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jig is always needed. Jig provides the replica of actual task."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Which of the following has higher production rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) table top drill",
            "b) gang drill",
            "c) column drill",
            "d) turret drill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Turret drill has higher production rate compare to others. This turret word is derived from Italian word torretta which means a tower."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Turret drill generally has ______ axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Turret drill generally has vertical axis. It has it axis along with y axis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "In turret drill, which of the following is mounted in holes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) boring tool",
            "b) ream cutter",
            "c) countersinking tool",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily seen from the construction of this machine. The drills are mounted in holes while the table is used for the fixing of jobs."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "A job is mounted______ in turret drill.",
        "Options": [
            "a) on table",
            "b) in holes",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All can be mounted in holes. Turret drill is a versatile tool. It can enlarge the drill and perform number of operations. For that purpose, all mentioned types of tools can be mounted in holes."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "In turret drill, table can move______",
        "Options": [
            "a) in x direction",
            "b) in y direction",
            "c) either in x direction or in y direction",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A job is mounted on table in turret drill. At the same time, tools are mounted in holes."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which type of operation is possible in turret drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) secondary enlargement",
            "b) thrust enlargement",
            "c) both secondary enlargement and thrust enlargement",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The table can move either in x direction or in y direction in order to accommodate with work."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "In turret drill, table moment can be_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mechanical",
            "b) hydraulic",
            "c) electrohydraulic",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The entire turret can move vertically up and down along with drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Multi spindle drilling machine can be categorized as_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) general purpose drilling machine",
            "b) special purpose drilling machine",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Multi spindle drilling is used to make drill in a huge number at a time-simultaneously. So this machine can be used for lot production."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for multi spindle drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it can’t make number of  holes at different location and of different size",
            "b) it is able to make number of  holes at different location and of different size",
            "c) it can’t make number of  holes at different location , but can make holes of different size",
            "d) it can make number of  holes at different location , but can not make holes of different size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a special purpose drilling machine. It is not used for general purpose. It is used when we need to make a lot of holes simultaneously of different shape and different depth and again in mass production."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Multi spindle drill machines can produce holes of different______",
        "Options": [
            "a) shapes",
            "b) depth",
            "c) both shapes and depth",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the construction of this machine. Due to large number of spindles, it can makes a lot of holes simultaneously."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the part of multi spindle drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) motor",
            "b) central gear",
            "c) planetary gear",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This machine can make number of holes at different location and also of different sizes. This reduces the time of operations and also increases the accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "In multi spindle drill, the drills are used at______",
        "Options": [
            "a) same height",
            "b) different height",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It can produce variety of holes of different sizes and shapes. There are number of spindles which can perform simultaneously."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "The base of the micro drill is______",
        "Options": [
            "a) light",
            "b) heavy",
            "c) very light",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of micro drill machine. As the name suggest micro drill makes very small holes so it is also known as mini drill machine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "The base of the table is_____ in micro drill machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) free",
            "b) fixed",
            "c) either free or fixed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It doesn’t have height in terms of micrometers. It is very small that’s why it is termed as micro drill machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which type of motion is possible for drilling head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) up",
            "b) down",
            "c) up and down",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The base is generally heavy in this case. To make hole, drill needs a huge downward pressure. To sustain this pressure, base should be heavy. "
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "If the speed of the drill increases, then the thrust force will______",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase",
            "b) decrease",
            "c) remain same",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The base can be either free or fixed base on the job. But it should be strong to withstand high pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "If the speed of the drill decreases, then the torque will______",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase",
            "b) decrease",
            "c) remain same",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Drilling head can be moved up and down in order to accommodate with the job."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Which type of work can be done in micro drill machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fine work",
            "b) electrical work",
            "c) electro-fitting work",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the working of this machine. We don’t need manual support for the control of feed motion. The feed of a drill is the distance the drill moves into work at each revolution of the spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of following is necessary for deep hole?",
        "Options": [
            "a) l/d ratio should be high",
            "b) l/d ratio should be less",
            "c) l/d ratio should be same",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: L/d ratio should be very high for deep hole. Here l=length of the tool and d means diameter of the tool. If l/d ratio is high that means tool has large length compare to its diameter and then and then only it can make deep holes."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Where we need the deep hole?",
        "Options": [
            "a) barrel of guns",
            "b) both barrel of guns and oil holes in crank shaft",
            "c) oil holes in crank shaft",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We need the deep hole in all these application. Crank shaft is a machine responsible for conversion between reciprocating motion and rotary motion."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Which of the following problem we face with deep hole?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drill breakage",
            "b) poor cutting fluid action",
            "c) chip clogging",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all problems we face with deep hole. There are some chances that cutting fluid can not able to reach at the bottom at the drill, at that time chip can be clogged to the flute. This is chip clogging. "
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Deep hole drilling machines are normally______",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical",
            "b) horizontal",
            "c) 45 degree inclined to both horizontal and vertical axis",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is wrong. In deep hole, there should be large helix angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "In deep hole drill, high speed spindle________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reduce the cutting force",
            "b) increase the cutting force",
            "c) doesn’t affect the cutting force",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Deep hole drilling machines are normally horizontal. These machines have horizontal axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "In deep hole drill machine, the tool is_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) long",
            "b) slender",
            "c) long and slender",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High speed spindle reduces the cutting force. If the spindle move with fast speed, we need less cutting force."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Sensitive bench drilling machine is used for____",
        "Options": [
            "a) heavy work",
            "b) light work",
            "c) both heavy and light work",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Sensitive bench drilling machine is small in size."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": " Sensitive bench drilling machine is capable of drilling holes up to ______ mm diameter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.25",
            "b) 12.5",
            "c) 2.5",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is used only for light work as it is not a big machine. It is comparatively small machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the part of sensitive bench drilling machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) driving motor",
            "b) cone pulley",
            "c) sleeve",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It can drill up to 12.5 mm diameter as it is only used for small work, not for heavy work."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "The base of the sensitive bench drilling machine is____",
        "Options": [
            "a) free",
            "b) mounted on a bench",
            "c) rotary",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. For normal drilling, the work surface is kept horizontal."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "In sensitive bench drilling machine, the drills are fitted in ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) chuck",
            "b) spindle",
            "c) either in chuck or in spindle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the simplest type of drilling machine as it is very small and again used for only light work."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about sensitive bench drilling machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) different spindle speeds can be achieved",
            "b) we can change the position of belt in the stepped pulley",
            "c) there is some space between the work table and base",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are the parts of this machine. Apart from these, chuck, spindle lock, deep gauge and stop, belt guard etc. are also the part of this machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation, we can’t perform on drilling machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) reaming",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) lapping",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Although drilling is primarily intended for drill but now it becomes a versatile tool. It can perform various operations including reaming, tapping, lapping and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Tapping attachment is included in_______ method of tool holding devices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) by chucks",
            "b) by a sleeve",
            "c) by directly fitting in the spindle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is included in special attachment method. In tapping, one end is always thinner than other end."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Floating holder is included in______ method of tool holding devices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) by directly fitting in the spindle",
            "b) by special attachments",
            "c) by a socket",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is included in special attachment. Floating holder is a type of holder that permits certain amount freedom to enable the tool  with a purpose of maintaining a proper path relative to the work."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is not used for holding tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) by a sleeve",
            "b) by chucks",
            "c) by a socket",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These all methods are used for holding tools. There are various types of chucks 2 jaw chuck, three jaw chuck etc. Sleeve and socket are also used for this purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which of the following device is not used for holding the work in a drilling machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) step block",
            "b) drill jigs",
            "c) both step block and drill jigs",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. Now, drill machine becomes a versatile tool. We can perform grinding operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "The drilling machine was primarily designed to originate a _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat surface",
            "b) cylindrical surface",
            "c) taper surface",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Both are used for holding the work in drilling machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "For drilling operation, the drill rotates with_____ pressure if job is held on earth.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upward",
            "b) downward",
            "c) 45 degree inclined to both planes",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Work shouldn’t be held by hand as it may causes injuries to the operator."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "According to material, drill can be classified as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) hss",
            "b) carbides",
            "c) bot hss and carbides",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both hss and carbides are classified according to material. In carbides, generally cemented carbide is mostly used."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "HSS was introduced in______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1895",
            "b) 1905",
            "c) 1915",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HSS is the acronym form of high speed steel. It is commonly used in tool bits and cutting tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which of the following element is included in HSS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tungsten",
            "b) chromium",
            "c) both tungsten and chromium",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It was introduced in 1915. It was introduced in U.S.A."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "How much chromium is there in HSS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 14",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: F.W. Taylor introduced the HSS. Full name of F.M. Taylor is Frederick Winslow Taylor."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "How much tungsten is there in HSS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 14",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both are included in HSS. Apart from tungsten and chromium, carbon and manganese are also included in HSS."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Which of the following quality does HSS has?",
        "Options": [
            "a) toughness",
            "b) formability",
            "c) tensile strength",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the structure of HSS. In the starting mn was used but because of its some drawbacks cr took its place and today it is used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Which of the following drill is produced power metallurgically?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hss",
            "b) cemented carbides",
            "c) diamond",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: About 18% tungsten is there in HSS. HSS gain its most of property from tungsten and molybdenum."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "According to size, drill can be classified as______",
        "Options": [
            "a) micro drill",
            "b) moderate drill",
            "c) large drill",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Micro drill, moderate drill and large drill are the types of drill according to size. Generally, this size is expressed in micron or in mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "When the size of the drill is around 25 to 500 micron,________ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) micro drill",
            "b) moderate drill",
            "c) large drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Micro drill has a size from 25 to 500 micron as per classification."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "When the size of the drill is around 3 to 25 mm,________ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) micro drill",
            "b) moderate drill",
            "c) large drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Moderate drill has a size of 3 to 25 mm as per the classification."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "When the size of the drill is around 25 to 40 mm,________ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) micro drill",
            "b) moderate drill",
            "c) large drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally, the large drill drill has a size from 25 to 40 mm as per classification."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Which of the following drill is most widely used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) micro drill",
            "b) moderate drill",
            "c) large drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Moderate type of drill is most widely used as it has medium size of drill- not too large and not too short."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "1 mm = ______ micron.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 100",
            "c) 1000",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is the simple mathematical conversion. 1 mm = 1000 micron and 1 micron = 0.001 mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "In industry, which type of drill is most useful?",
        "Options": [
            "a) micro drill",
            "b) moderate drill",
            "c) large drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Large drills need large force as it has large l/d ratio. "
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "For large drill, how much torque is needed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) moderate",
            "c) large",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In industry, moderate type of drill is most widely used as it has medium size of drill and again it doesn’t need large force like large drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used for mass production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) micro drill",
            "b) moderate drill",
            "c) large drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For large drill large force is needed. As torque=force*displacement so torque is directly proportional to the force. So we need large torque for large drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Which of the following is most commonly used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single flute drill",
            "b) two flute drill",
            "c) three or four flute drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the property of it.  There is a sharp blade which is there along with edge of the flute known as teeth."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Which of the following is rarely used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single flute drill",
            "b) two flute drill",
            "c) three or four flute drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Two flute drill is commonly used because it is very versatile and has wide applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Single flute drill is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) very light",
            "b) very rigid",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Single flute drill is rarely used as it has very limited applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the example of single flute drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) deep hole drill",
            "b) crank shaft hole drill",
            "c) both deep hole drill and crank shaft hole drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is very rigid that’s the reason why it has very small applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as slot drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single flute drill",
            "b) two flute drill",
            "c) three or four flute drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both are examples of single flute drill. Deep hole drilling is used with large length and comparatively small diameter of drill. Crank shaft hole drill has also wide applications. "
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Gun drill is the example of______",
        "Options": [
            "a) single flute drill",
            "b) two flute drill",
            "c) three or four flute drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally 3 or 4 flute drill is also known as slot drill. Slot drill is a double cutting drill with flat end. It has two radial cutting edges."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "For cutting ductile material with a long chip, ______ helixangle is necessary.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) moderate",
            "c) long",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. The angle between the helix and axial line on the right is known as helix angel."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Large helix angle ensures the _______ in cutting force.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increment",
            "b) reduction",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Long helix angle is used for cutting ductile materials with a long chip."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "For spade drill, ______ helix angle is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) large",
            "c) zero",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the property of it. Helix angles are used in power transfer and in motion conversation in mechanical engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "For hard materials, ______ helix angle is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) large",
            "c) zero",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Zero helix angle is used for this purpose.Spade drill is a two fluted drill.  The external flute provide efficient chip removal."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "For micro drill, ______ helix angle is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) large",
            "c) zero",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Small helix angle is used for this purpose. In screws, helical gears and warm gears, we uses this helix angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Which helix angle is used for deep hole drilling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) large",
            "c) zero",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Zero helix angel is used for this purpose. Helix angel is like a angel between tangent to a helix and an axial line on the right. "
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Which helix angle is used for making holes in very soft materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) small",
            "b) large",
            "c) zero",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Large helix angel is used for this purpose. Zero helix angel are used for small drilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "According to the helix angel of the flutes, drill can be classified as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) small helix",
            "b) large helix",
            "c) zero helix",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Large helix angel is used for this purpose as it can make make deep holes easily without any extra effort."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "If we increase the helix angle, strength of drill will______",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase",
            "b) decrease",
            "c) not affected",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Drill can be classified in number of ways. based on helix angel, based on number of flutes, based on materials, based on size on so on. Based on helix angel, it can be classified as small helix, large helix and zero helix."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "11.Chip disposal will be better If we _______ the helix angle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase",
            "b) decrease",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is an inverse relationship between helix angel and strength of drill. If we increase the helix angel, strength of drill will decrease and vice versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "What is the range of the usual helix angle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 25",
            "b) 20 to 35",
            "c) 45 to 60",
            "d)none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the property of helix angel and if we decrease the helix angel it will affect chip disposal rate in a negative way."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "What is the range of the large helix angle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 25",
            "b) 20 to 35",
            "c) 45 to 60",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 20 to 35-This is the usual range for usual helix angel."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "If we increase the helix angle, rack angle will______",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase",
            "b) decrease",
            "c) not affected",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 45 to 60-This is the usual range for usual helix angel."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "If l/d ratio is too large, then drill becomes_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) weak",
            "b) strong",
            "c) very sharp",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The large l/d ratio weaken the drill. If we have very long drill with small diameter then it can’t perform drilling operation more accurately."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "For general purpose, l/d ratio should be_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 to 10",
            "b) 10 to 20",
            "c) more than 20",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chip removal will be difficult if this ratio is too short. Short l/d ratio weakens the drilling and reduce the performance. So the chip removal will be difficult. "
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which of the following can also be termed as center drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) general drill",
            "b) short drill",
            "c) long drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of long drill. Long drills has high l/d ration. So it can make high deeply holes."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "According to the shank type, drill can be classified as______",
        "Options": [
            "a) straight shank",
            "b) taper shank",
            "c) both taper shank and straight shank",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For general purpose, the ratio should be 5 to 10. The drills containing these ratio generally used in ordinary performances."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "In ______ type, drill is held in spindle directly.",
        "Options": [
            "a) straight shank",
            "b) taper shank",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Short drill can also be termed as centerr drill. "
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "In _______ type, drill is held in chuck.",
        "Options": [
            "a) straight shank",
            "b) taper shank",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For long drills, this ratio should be more than 25. For general purpose it should have ratio of 5 to 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "According to specific use, drill can be classified as______",
        "Options": [
            "a) center drill",
            "b) step drill",
            "c) both center drill and step drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both are the examples of specific use drill. These special purpose drilling machines are intended for drilling multiple holes at a single setting."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Subland drill is type of drill according to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) l/d ratio",
            "b) shank type",
            "c) specific use",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Subland drill is the example of special purpose drilling machine. Apart from this, turret, micro drill press and muliple spindle drilling machines are also an example of specific purpose drilling machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following drill is very short drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) center drill",
            "b) subland drill",
            "c) step drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Center drill is very short drill. Subland drill and step drill are large as compare to center drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for center drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the hole is used to support the center",
            "b) it is the type of drill according to specific use",
            "c) one taper has to be made here",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the mentioned sentences are true. It has a taper and also it is a specific purpose drill machine. It is short drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "In center drill, center has to be mounted on______",
        "Options": [
            "a) headstock",
            "b) tailstock",
            "c) headstock or tailstock",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The center can be mounted on either headstock or tailstock. Headstock and tailstock both are mounted on the bed."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "In which of the following, l/d ratio is very long?",
        "Options": [
            "a) half round drill",
            "b) gun drill",
            "c) both half round drill and gun drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Here l=length and d=diameter. In both half round drill and gun drill this ratio is very long as they have large value of length as compare to diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "How many cutting edges are there in half round drill and gun drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) may be one or two",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One edge is there in these both half round drill and gun drill. In these both drills, diameter is less as compare to length."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "How many flutes are there in half round drill and gun drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) may be one or two",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One or two flutes are there in these both machines. These both machines are specific purpose machines used for a specific purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a pipe like cutting tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) center drill",
            "b) half round drill",
            "c) gun drill",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The base is very strong in half round drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the cutting parameters used in drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cutting speed",
            "b) feed",
            "c) depth of cut",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are the cutting parameters used in drill. Apart from these parameters, machining time, metal removal rate are also cutting parameters which are used in drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered as the peripheral speed of the drill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cutting speed",
            "b) feed",
            "c) depth of cut",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the definition of cutting speed. If you know the diameter of the drill and rpm of the drill, you can easily calculate the cutting speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Cutting speed generally express in_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) meter",
            "b) meter/minute",
            "c) meter*minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cutting speed is simply a speed. So, its unit should be match with speed’s unit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "The ______ of a drill is the distance the drill moves into the work at each revolution of the spindle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) depth of cut",
            "b) feed",
            "c) cutting speed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Though cutting speed is peripheral speed the distance covered through it must be equal to 3.14*d. N is rpm and 1000 is there as we are measuring it in mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "The feed may be expressed in______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm/revolution",
            "b) mm*revolution",
            "c) mm",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the definition of feed. It is a distance/revolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "______ is equal to half the diameter of the drill used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) feed",
            "b) depth of cut",
            "c) machining time",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per its definition, feed is the distance per revolution. So its unit should be match with this formula.."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "Depth of cut can be expressed in______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm",
            "b) mm/revolution",
            "c) mm/minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the definition of depth of cut. Its simply a distance. Here one point is there, we always talk in terms of diameter in drill, never in terms of radius."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Machining time is expressed in______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm/minute",
            "b) minute*minute",
            "c) minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is simply a distance and so its unit should be match with distance’s unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "If l=length of travel of the drill in mm, n=rpm of the drill, s= feed per revolution of the drill in mm. Then machining time can be given as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) (l*n)/s",
            "b) (l*s)/n",
            "c) l/(n*s)",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Depth of cut is equal to half the diameter of the drill used. So if d is the diameter of drill then its formula must be equal to d/2.."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Metal removal rate can be given as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) (mm*mm*mm)/min",
            "b) (mm*mm*m)/revolution",
            "c) mm/revolution",
            "d) mm/minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be solved by equating units both sides. Left side unit = feed/minute and Right side unit = feed / revolution * revolution/minute. So overall unit of right side = feed/minute. So, left side unit=right side unit.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation is performed to ensure the correct location of a hole by making it concentric with the axis of rotation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) parting",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) boring",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is the characteristic of boring. After the hole is made by drilling operation, boring is carried out. It is generally done to enlarge the diameter of the hole."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Which of the following operations can be done by same tool?",
        "Options": [
            "a) reaming and tapping",
            "b) drilling and facing",
            "c) counterboring and spot facing",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Counterboring and spot facing can be performed by same tool. Counter boring is an operation which nis carried out for providing recess for nuts or bolt heads."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is performed to provide seating for washer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) counterboring",
            "b) spot facing",
            "c) tapping",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reaming improves the surface finish. It generally enlarge the holes with great accuracy and give better dimensional accuracy-better surface finish."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "To produce more accurate holes, which of the following operation should be performed first?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) reaming",
            "c) centering",
            "d) boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the definition of spot facing process. In spot facing operation, some specific part of the workpiece is faced. It gives better flat,smooth surface to that workpiece."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "To produce more accurate holes, which of the following operation should be performed last?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) reaming",
            "c) centering",
            "d) boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As per the characteristic of all these operation, centering should be performed first before drilling, reaming and boring in order to produce more accurate holes. Center drill makes a hole. Now, this hole behave as a center of rotation for mentioned rest 3 operations."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Which of the following process requires abundant coolant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) boring",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: As per the characteristic of all these operation, reaming should be performed last in order to produce more accurate holes. By using all rest 3 method, we make the hole with almost accuracy. But for final finish and extremely high accuracy, reaming is performed at the last."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Tapping process is carried out on ______ machines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) both drilling and tapping",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of taping process. The main advantage of taping is that is requires less operating conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation is carried out for cutting internal threads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) boring",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tapping needs abundant coolant. Cutting fluid is the coolant generally designed for metal working process.Different types of fluids are there like oil, gel, aerosols and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation is carried out to make the hole dimensionally more accurate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) reaming",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) boring",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of this process. A tap is also applied for cutting and forming female part of the mating pair like nuts."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation is performed to provide recess for bolt heads or nuts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) counterboring",
            "b) spot facing",
            "c) tapping",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reaming is used for this purpose. Reaming also improve the surface finish which is its extra advantage."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is carried out to provide seating for head of screw?",
        "Options": [
            "a) counterboring",
            "b) countersinking",
            "c) tapping",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of counterboring process. Generally, counter boring is a process carried out for delivering recess for nuts etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "To produce more accurate holes, which of the following operation should be performed third?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) reaming",
            "c) centering",
            "d) boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is carried out by a reamer. Reamer is a cutting tool generally used for enlarging the hole with great accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "To produce more accurate holes, which of the following operation should be performed second?",
        "Options": [
            "a) drilling",
            "b) reaming",
            "c) centering",
            "d) boring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the definition of countersinking process. To make the cone or taper shape at the entrance of the hole, this process is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation is used to enlarge the previously drilled hole?",
        "Options": [
            "a) reaming",
            "b) tapping",
            "c) boring",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Countersink tool is used for countersinking process. Counter sinks are available as single flute and and multi flute tools."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "A hole is being drilled with 5 mm drill at a feed of 0.1 mm/revolution and rpm is 200. Calculate the metal removal rate (m) in mm3/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 392.5",
            "b) 785",
            "c) 1570",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here, we have the value of diameter, feed and rpm. So, from the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4, we can easily get the value of metal removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "If drill is 2.5 mm, feed is 0.35 mm/revolution and metal removal rate is 40 mm3/minute. Then find out the value of rpm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 46.6",
            "b) 23.3",
            "c) 93.2",
            "d) 11.65"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4. From this formula, we can easily calculate rpm. Rpm means revolution per minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "If drill is 5.5 mm, metal removal rate is 65 mm3/minute and rpm is 130.Then find the value of feed in mm/revolution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.02",
            "b) 0.2",
            "c) 0.04",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Feed is the distance the drill moves into the work at each revolution of the spindle. From the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4, we can easily calculate feed."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "If metal removal rate is 120 mm3/minute, rpm is 105 and feed is 0.1 mm/revolution. Then find the value of drill in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14.6",
            "b) 3.8",
            "c) 7.6",
            "d) 1.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4, we can calculate the value of drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "If value of the diameter of the drill (d2) = 10mm, then find the value of the depth of cut (d1).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 20",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Value of diameter of the drill is always twice to that the value of the depth of cut. From the formula, d1= d2/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "The diameter of the drill is 15 mm and rpm of drill is 5. Find the value of cutting speed in meter/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 235.5",
            "b) 0.2355",
            "c) 0.075",
            "d) 75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, cs = (3.14*d*n) /1000. Cutting speed is the peripheral speed of the drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": " Rpm is 10 and feed per revolution (f2) is 5. Then find the value of feed per minute (f1).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 1",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rpm = f1/f2. Here rpm=10 and f2=5. So value of f1 should be 50."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "If depth of cut is 20 mm, then find the value of diameter of the drill.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 40",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depth of cut=diameter/2. It is simply a distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Feed per minute (f1) is 20 and rpm (n) is 5. Then find the value of feed per revolution (f2).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rpm = f1/f2. Here f1=20 and n=5. So, f2 should be 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "If t=2minute, n=2rpm and s=5 mm. Then find the value of l. t=machining time in minute, l=length of travel of the drill in mm, n= rpm of the drill and s=feed per revolution of the drill in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 20",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l / (n*s). Here t=2, n=2 and s=5. Put all these values with their units in the mentioned equation,you will easily get the answer as 20 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "If d=2, n=1 and f=2. Then find the value of m. d= diameter of drill in mm, n=rpm, f=feed per revolution in mm and m=metal removal rate in mm3/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.14",
            "b) 6.28",
            "c) 12.56",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, m= (3.14*d*d*n*f) / 4, we can easily get the value of m. Metal removal rate means the rate at which the metal is removed during the operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "If d=2, n=2 and m=3. Then find the value of f. d= diameter of drill in mm, n=rpm, f=feed per revolution in mm and m=metal removal rate in mm3/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.238",
            "b) 0.477",
            "c) 0.119",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, m= (3.14*d*d*n*f) / 4, we can easily get the value of feed. Feed may also be expressed as feet per minute or mm/minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "If m=5, n=2 and f=3. Then find the value of m. d= diameter of drill in mm, n=rpm, f=feed per revolution in mm and m=metal removal rate in mm3/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.03",
            "b) 1.065",
            "c) 0.266",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, m= (3.14*d*d*n*f) / 4, we can easily find the value of m."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "If cs=0.942 and d=60, then find the value of n. d=diameter of drill in mm, n=rpm and cs=cutting speed in mm/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15.7",
            "b) 15700",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 5000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the formula, cs = (3.14*d*n) /1000, we can easily find value of n. N means rpm-revolution per minute. It is an important term in any operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "A hole is being drilled with 1.5mm drill at a feed of 0.3 mm/revolution and rpm is 70. Calculate the metal removal rate in mm3/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18.5",
            "b) 37",
            "c) 74",
            "d) 148"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metal removal rate means the rate at which the metal is removed during the operation. From the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4, we can easily calculate metal removal rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "If drill is 2 mm, feed is 0.2 mm/revolution and metal removal rate is 50 mm^/minute. Then find out the value of rpm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 318.4",
            "b) 159.2",
            "c) 79.6",
            "d) 39.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4. Put all the given values with their respective units in the above equation and you will get the value of n as 79.6 ."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "If drill is 3.15 mm, metal removal rate is 55 mm3/minute and rpm is 170.Then find the value of feed in mm/revolution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.02",
            "b) 0.2",
            "c) 0.04",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During each revolution of spindle drill moves into the work. That distance is known as the feed.From the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "If metal removal rate is 100 mm3/minute, rpm is 165 and feed is 0.01 mm/revolution. Then find the value of drill in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.78",
            "b) 4.41",
            "c) 19.3",
            "d) 77.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the formula, m= ( 3.14*d*d*f*n) / 4. By substituting all the given values in the above equation, we can easily get the value of drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "If diameter of the drill is 20 mm. Then find the value of depth of cut in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 40",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Depth of cut=diameter/2. Depth of cut is equal to half the diameter of the drill used."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "The diameter of the drill is 20 mm and rpm of drill is 10. Find the value of cutting speed in meter/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.628",
            "b) 628",
            "c) 0.2",
            "d) 200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the formula, cs = (3.14*d*n) /1000. Cutting speed in a drilling operation is taken as the peripheral speed of the drill."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": " Feed per minute (f1) is 10 and feed per revolution (f2) is 5. Then find the value of rpm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rpm = f1/f2. Here, f1=10 and f2=5. We can easily get the value of rpm as 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "If the depth of cut (d1) is 10mm, then find the value of the diameter of the drill (d2).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 20",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the formula, d1= d2/2. Here d1=10. So, d2 sholud be 5."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "If l=10mm, n=2 rpm and s=5 mm. Then find the value of t. t=machining time in minute, l=length of travel of the drill in mm, n= rpm of the drill and s=feed per revolution of the drill in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l / (n*s). By putting all the given values in the above equation, we can easily get the value of machining time as 1 minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "If l=10mm, n=2 rpm and t=0.5 minute. Then find the value of s. t=machining time in minute, l=length of travel of the drill in mm, n= rpm of the drill and s=feed per revolution of the drill in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 20",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l / (n*s), we can calculate the feed per revolution. Feed per revolution may be defined as the axial distance moved by the drill into the work per revolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "If l=20 mm, t=2 minute and s=5 mm. Then find the value of t. t=machining time in minute, l=length of travel of the drill in mm, n= rpm of the drill and s=feed per revolution of the drill in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l / (n*s). Substitute all the given values in the above equation and you can get the value of t as 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "If d=1, n=1 and f=4. Then find the value of m. d= diameter of drill in mm, n=rpm, f=feed per revolution in mm and m=metal removal rate in mm3/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.08",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0.3184",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the formula, m= (3.14*d*d*n*f) / 4. Here d,n and f are given. Substitute these values in above equation, you will easily get value of m as 0.3184 ."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "If d=2, n=4 and f=1. Then find the value of m. d= diameter of drill in mm, n=rpm, f=feed per revolution in mm and m=metal removal rate in mm3/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.798",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0.6369",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the formula, m= (3.14*d*d*n*f) / 4. Substitute all tyhe given values in the above equation and you will easily get the value."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "If cs=1 and n=40, then find the value of d. d=diameter of drill in mm, n=rpm and cs=cutting speed in mm/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.96",
            "b) 3.98",
            "c) 15.92",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the formula, cs = (3.14*d*n) /1000. Substitute all tyhe given values in the above equation and you will easily get the value of d."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for machining larger jobs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) shaper",
            "b) planer",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Planer is used for the purpose of machining too large and heavy jobs. There is a table in planer known as platen on which the work piece is fixed firmly and the operation is performed."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for machining smaller jobs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) shaper",
            "b) planer",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Shaper is used for the purpose of machining smaller jobs. It is mainly used for producing flat and plan surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Which of the following machine is primarily intended for producing flat surfaces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) shaper",
            "b) drilling",
            "c) lathe",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shaper is intended for this purpose. It was invented in 1836 by James Nasmyth."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Which of the following operation can be performed in shaper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gear cutting",
            "b) keyways cutting",
            "c) curvilinear contours",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All mentioned operations can be performed in shaper. Although it is used mainly for producing flat surfaces but its a versatile machine and can be used for other purposes too."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "In shaper, the job is kept_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) stationary",
            "b) rotating",
            "c) reciprocating",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The job is kept stationary in this machine. In shaper, cutting tool moves in order to perform operations."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Which stroke is cutting stroke in shaper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) forward",
            "b) return",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. cutting tool moves in order to perform the work. Only forward movement is useful. Work is only done in forward movement. "
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which stroke is idle stroke in shaper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) forward",
            "b) return",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Forward stroke is cutting stroke in shaper because only in forward stroke work-cutting is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "At the end of one cycle, job is given a feed motion______ to the direction of tool movement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) anti-parallel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Return stroke is idle stroke in shaper because no useful work is done in this stroke."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "In shaper, the tool head consists of_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) tool post",
            "b) tool slide",
            "c) clamper box",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All mentioned are the parts of tool head. Toolhead of a shaper holds the tool rigidly and provides vertical and angular feed movement."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "The main parts of shaper are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) base and body",
            "b) ram and tool head",
            "c) crossrail and body",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All mentioned are the parts of shaper. Due to these parts, this machine is arranged in such a manner that it can produce flat surfaces easily and perform other operations too."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "The body of the shaper comprises of  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pillar",
            "b) column",
            "c) frame",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All are the parts of shaper. Column and pillar are used to stabilize the machine and are mounted on base. The frame is the basic structure of this machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of the following part of shaper supports the entire load of the machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) base",
            "b) crossrail",
            "c) frame",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the construction of the base. It must be made of heavy cast iron casting because the whole machine including pillar, frame, column are mounted on the base. So base must be capable and strong enough to withstand it."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Drive mechanism consists of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) main drives",
            "b) the gear box",
            "c) quick return mechanism",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Base of shaper supports the entire load of the machine. All other parts are mounted on the base. It is the basic foundation of this machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "The top of the body provides guideways for______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ram",
            "b) crossrail",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The base of shaper is able to withstand the vibration. In shaper, reciprocating feed is given so there is always a chance of higher vibration and since the entire machine is mounted on the base it is necessary that this base must be able to withstand vibration for the safety purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "The front of the body provides guideways for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ram",
            "b) crossrail",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The front of the body provides guideways for crossrail . Crossrail has two parallel guideways on its top in the vertical plane."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The crossrail is mounted on the______ of the body frame",
        "Options": [
            "a) front",
            "b) back",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The crossrail is mounted on the front of the body frame. Crossrail can slide up and down in the vertical frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The _______ movements of crossrail permit the jobs of different heights to be accommodated below the tool.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: These both movements are possible in the ram. It houses a screwed shaft for altering the position of ram."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Which movement of ram is called stroke?",
        "Options": [
            "a) only back",
            "b) only forth",
            "c) back and forth",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The vertical movements of crossrail permit the jobs of different heights to be accommodated below the tool. The table may be raised or lowered to accommodate different sizes of job by rotating an elevating screw which causes the crossrail to slide up and down."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Shaper can produce contours of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) concave",
            "b) convex",
            "c) both concave and convex",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is true. It carries the table which can be raised or lowered to accommodate different sizes."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "According to the type of mechanism used for giving reciprocating motion to the ram, shaper can be classified as______",
        "Options": [
            "a) crank type",
            "b) geared type",
            "c) both crank type and geared type",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to the type of mechanism used for giving reciprocating motion to the ram, shaper can be classified as both crank type and geared type. Here the ram means the reciprocating member of the shaper which houses a screwed shaft. "
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "According to the type of design of the table, lathe can be classified as_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) standard shaper",
            "b) universal shape",
            "c) both standard shaper and universal shaper",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to the type of design of the table, lathe can be classified as both standar shaper and universal shaper. Standard shaper is also known as plain shaper  which has only two movements vertical and horizontal to get feed."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Push type shaper is type of shaper according to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) design of the table",
            "b) position and travel of the ram",
            "c) type of cutting stroke",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Push type shaper is type of shaper according to type of cutting stroke. In push type shaper, at the time when the ram is moving away/going away from the column, removal of metal is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "horizontal type shaper is type of shaper according to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) design of the table",
            "b) position and travel of the ram",
            "c) type of cutting stroke",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: horizontal type shaper is type of shaper according to position and travel of the ram. When we talk about horizontal shaper, it is mostly used for producing flat surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Draw type shaper is type of shaper according to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) design of the table",
            "b) position and travel of the ram",
            "c) type of cutting stroke",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Draw type shaper is type of shaper according to, type of cutting stroke. In this type of shaper, at the time when the ram is moving towards in the direction of column, the metal removal is done. "
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Travelling head type shaper is type of shaper according to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) design of the table",
            "b) position and travel of the ram",
            "c) type of cutting stroke",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Travelling head type shaper is type of shaper according to, position and travel of the ram. In workshop, if we have a machine that cannot be fixed on the machine or can not be moved at that time we use this shaper."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Hydraulic type shaper is type of shaper according to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) design of the table",
            "b) position and travel of the ram",
            "c) type of cutting stroke",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per the classification of this machine, it can be classified according to the type of mechanism used for giving reciprocal motion to the ram. In hydraulic shaper, not a penny sound is produced. So this shaper machine can be termed as eco friendly machine to some extent."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Vertical type shaper is type of shaper according to______",
        "Options": [
            "a) design of the table",
            "b) position and travel of the ram",
            "c) type of cutting stroke",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is false. In crank type shaper, for performing an operation a SINGLE point cutting tool is employed. The crank mechanism is used in order to drive reciprocating ram. "
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "A shaper is termed as standard when the table has _____ movements.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only one",
            "b) only two",
            "c) only three",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of standard shaper. This shaper uses a linear tool path for machining. "
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which type of movements of table can be given to the feed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) horizontal or vertical",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the definition of standard shaper. Other types of shaper are horizontal shaper, draw-cut shaper, universal shaper etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "The base of the standard shaper is able to_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) resist vibration",
            "b) take up high compressive",
            "c) both resist vibration and take up high compressive",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both horizontal and vertical table movements can be given to feed. Linear relative motion between a work piece and single point cutting tool is given.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a box like casting mounted  up on the base.",
        "Options": [
            "a) column",
            "b) crossrail",
            "c) toolhead",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is not compulsory that the must be supported at the outer end. It may or may not be supported at outer end."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Which of the following encloses the ram drive mechanism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) crossrail",
            "b) toolhead",
            "c) saddle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the construction of shaper machine, it may be made of cast iron as it provide great strength and stability."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": " How many machined guideways are provided on the top of the column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) four",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is the property of standard shaper’s base. As it is made of cast iron and other strong component it has these properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "The _____ face of the column serves as the guideways for the crossrail.",
        "Options": [
            "a) front horizontal",
            "b) back horizontal",
            "c) front vertical",
            "d) back vertical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the construction of standard shaper. This type of arrangement of base provide great stability to machine and make the machine more suitable for its purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Which type of feed movements of tool does the toolhead provide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical",
            "b) angular",
            "c) both vertical and angular",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Column is situated on the base so we can feel that it is a box like casting mounted up on the base because of its arrangement."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Which of the following part does column contain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lever",
            "b) handle",
            "c) both lever and handle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Column includes both lever and handle for operating the machine. Lever and handle are used to operate a machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "How many guideways does crossrail has on its top?",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) three",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crossrail has two guideways on its top. Guideways are a track or rail or path which are used along with movement."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "The guideways are ______ to the ram axis in crossrail.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) 45 degree inclined",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crossrail doesn’t has parallel guideways on its top in horizontal but it has guideways on its top in vertical plane."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "The horizontal cross feed screw is fitted _____ to the top guideways.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) horizontal",
            "c) 45 degree inclined",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the construction of the crossrail. Guideways are generally a path which are used for movement."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Elevating screw causes the crossrail to slide up and down on the____ face of the column.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) bottom",
            "d) top"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is fitted parallel to the top guideways. Cross feed is a type of feeding mechanism which acts transversely with respect to the longitudinal axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "The saddle is mounted on _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) ram",
            "b) toolhead",
            "c) column",
            "d) crossrail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: This is false. The horizontal cross feed screw actuates the table to move in a crosswise direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "The cross feed screw can be rotated by_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) hand",
            "b) power",
            "c) both hand or power",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the working of the crossrail. The vertical motion of table is possible in crossrail so that the table can be adjusted for different size of work and can perform more better."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Which type of movement does table receives?",
        "Options": [
            "a) only crosswise",
            "b) only vertical",
            "c) both crosswise and vertical",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Elevating screws enables vertical motion of crossrail. hence crossrail can easily slide up and down on the vertical face of the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "In a shaper_____ movement of the drive is converted into _____ movement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) rotary, reciprocating",
            "b) reciprocating, rotary",
            "c) rotary, rotary",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rotary movement of the drive is converted into reciprocating movement.Rotary motion is something like wheel turning and reciprocating motion means back and forth linear mtioon."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The usual size of shaper varies from _____ mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75 to 90",
            "b) 175 to 900",
            "c) 25 to 60",
            "d) 125 to 600"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the property of shaper. Here the ram is the reciprocating member of the shaper."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The change of the movement of the drive is done by the mechanism contained within the _____ of the machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) crossrail",
            "b) column",
            "c) toolhead",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The usual size of shaper ranges from 175 mm to 900 mm basede upon its application and working."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "The ram holding the tool gets _____ movement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) rotary",
            "b) reciprocating",
            "c) both rotary and reciprocating",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the function of column. Column is a part of shaper which is mounted on the base."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "In a standard shaper, the metal is removed in_____ stroke.",
        "Options": [
            "a) forward",
            "b) return",
            "c) both forward and return",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It gets reciprocating movement.Rotary motion is something like wheel turning and reciprocating motion means back and forth linear mtioon. "
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "To reduce the total cutting time, the standard shaper is designed to complete forward stroke______",
        "Options": [
            "a) slowly",
            "b) faster",
            "c) at moderate speed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The metal is removed in forward stroke because only in forward stroke the useful work is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "To reduce the total cutting time, the standard shaper is designed to complete return stroke______",
        "Options": [
            "a) slowly",
            "b) faster",
            "c) at moderate speed",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the desired property for standard shaper because only in forward stroke the useful work is done. So it should be slower than return stroke."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Quick return mechanism and reciprocating movement of the ram is obtained in _____ mechanism.",
        "Options": [
            "a) crank and slotted link mechanism",
            "b) whithworth quick return mechanism",
            "c) hydraulic shaper mechanism",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In return stroke no useful work is done so to reduce cutting time it is advisable to complete the return stroke as fast as possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "In crank and slotted link mechanism, an electric motor _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) rotates at constant speed",
            "b) rotates at variable speed",
            "c) doesn’t rotates",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These both desired properties are obtained in all mentioned mechanisms. These are desired properties which is needed for any mechanism to perform more accurately and better."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "In shaper mechanism, adjustment to be made before machining are_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) ramp speed",
            "b) stroke adjustment",
            "c) position adjustment",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the function of bull gear. Here the slotted link means lever."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "The slide of the lever can move radially _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) inward",
            "b) outward",
            "c) inward or outward",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All these adjustment should be made before machining time in order to perform job more accurately and in a better way."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "In shaper mechanism, nearer the slide block to the center, _____ is the stroke.",
        "Options": [
            "a) smaller",
            "b) larger",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slide of the lever can move radially inward or outward. This is done in order to vary the radius of the crank."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "The feed screw of the table rotates through a small angel in a direction _____ to the ram.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) anti-parallel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the mechanism of shaper. Depending upon the length of the job to be shaped, stroke length must be adjusted."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "Which type of cutting parameters are there in shaper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) feed",
            "b) depth of cut",
            "c) machining time",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Feed, depth of cut, machining time all are cutting parameters. Apart from these, cutting speed and metal removal rate are also termed as cutting parameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "In shaper, cutting speed is expressed only in ______ stroke.",
        "Options": [
            "a) forward",
            "b) return",
            "c) both forward and return",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of this machine. The shaper is a reciprocating machine which works only in forward stroke."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "What is the unit of cutting speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) meter/minute",
            "b) meter2 /minute",
            "c) meter",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only in forward stroke, cutting speed is expressed because only in forward stroke useful work is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "If n=number of  strokes of the ram per minute or rpm of the bull wheel, l=length of the cutting stroke in mm, m= the ratio between return time to cutting time, then find the formula for cutting stroke.",
        "Options": [
            "a) n*l*m / 100",
            "b) n*l*(m+1) / 100",
            "c) (l*m) / (n*100)",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cutting speed is simply a speed. So its unit should be the unit of time. Here, meter/minute is more appropriate unit for cutting speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "The feed is always given at the ______ of the return stroke.",
        "Options": [
            "a) starting",
            "b) end",
            "c) both at the starting and at the end",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is quite difficult to calculate cutting speed as we have to measure the time required by the cutting stroke."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Feed is expressed in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm",
            "b) mm/minute",
            "c) minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the formula for calculating the cutting speed.It may be expressed as length (distance) / time."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Feed is in direction _______ to the axis of reciprocation of the arm per double stroke.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) 45 degree inclined to both planes",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the definition of feed. It is simply a distance measured with help of relative movement of tool or work."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": " Depth of cut is the _______ distance between machined surface and non-machined surface of the workpiece.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) 45 degree inclined to both planes",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Feed is in direction perpendicular to the axis of reciprocation of the arm per double stroke because only in this case we get the efficient feed and accuracy."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Depth of cut is expressed in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm",
            "b) mm/minute",
            "c) minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Depth of cut is thickness of metal that is removed in one cut. Depth of cut is always measured in one cut."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Depth of cut may be given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) tool head slide",
            "b) lifting the table",
            "c) both tool head slide or drifting the table",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is the perpendicular distance. Depth of cut is thickness of metal that is removed in one cut."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "If v=cutting speed, s= feed in mm, b=width of work in mm, m=the ratio between the return time to cutting time and l= length of the cutting stroke in mm. Then, find the formula for time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) (l*b*m) / ( 1000*v*s)",
            "b) (l*b*(1+m) ) / ( 1000*v*s)",
            "c) (l*b*v) / ( m*s*1000)",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Depth of cut is simply a distance and so its unit should be match with distance’s unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "What is the unit for machining time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) minute",
            "b) mm/minute",
            "c) mm",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Depth of cut may be given by tool head slide or lifting the table. These two methods are used because of its accuracy and good performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "If d=depth of cut in mm, f=feed in mm/stroke, n=stroke/min, l=length of stroke in mm, m= ratio of return stroke time to cutting stroke time, then find the formula for metal removal rate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) f*d*l*n*(m+1)",
            "b) f*d*l*n*m",
            "c) f*d*l*n*m/1000",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: (l*b(1+m))/ (1000*v*s)-It is the formula for machining time. Machining time is simply time taken by machine to perform the job."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "What is the unit of metal removal rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm2/minute",
            "b) mm3/minute",
            "c) mm/minute",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is simply a time and so its unit should match with time’s unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "If the length of the cutting stroke is 10 mm and time required by the cutting stroke is 5 second, then find the value of cutting speed in mm/second.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 4",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: C.S.=length / time. Here, length is 10 mm and time is 5 second. So by dividing 10 by 5 we can easily get the answer as 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "If l=5, b=5, t=0.4, v=3 and m= 2. Find the value of s. l=length of the cutting stroke in mm, b=width of the work in mm, s=feed in mm, v=cutting speed in mm/minute, m=the ratio between return time to cutting time and t=machining time in minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.025",
            "b) 0.0125",
            "c) 0.00625",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l*b*(m+1) / (1000*v*s). By putting all given values, we can easily get answer as 0.00625."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "If n=rpm of the bull wheel=2, l= length of the cutting stroke in mm=2.5mm and cutting speed = 0.5 mm/minute. m= the ratio between return time to cutting time. Then find the value of m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 9",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 99"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: C.S. = n*l* (1+m) / 100. Here, n=2, l=2.5, cs=0.5 and m can be found by putting these values in the above equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "If n=rpm of the bull wheel=4 ,cs =cutting speed=3mm/minute and m= the ratio between return time to cutting time= 5. Then find the value of length of cutting stroke (l) in mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 12.5",
            "d) 6.24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: C.S. = n*l* (1+m) / 100. Here, n=4, cs=3, m=5 and l can be found out by putting these values in above equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "If l=9, b=5, s=3, v=2 and t=0. 0375. Find the value of m. l=length of the cutting stroke in mm, b=width of the work in mm, s=feed in mm, v=cutting speed in mm/minute, m=the ratio between return time to cutting time and t=machining time in minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 10",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l*b*(m+1) / (1000*v*s) , m should be 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "If n=rpm of the bull wheel, cs =cutting speed=3.2mm/minute and m= the ratio between return time to cutting time= 3 and l=length of cutting stroke (l)=8mm. Find the value of n.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 12",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: C.S. = n*l* (1+m) / 100 and value of n should be 10 by putting all parameters in above equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "If l=10, b=5, s=4, v=3 and m= 2. Find the value of t. l=length of the cutting stroke in mm, b=width of the work in mm, s=feed in mm, v=cutting speed in mm/minute, m=the ratio between return time to cutting time and t=machining time in minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.025",
            "b) 0.0125",
            "c) 0.00625",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l*b*(m+1) / (1000*v*s), we can easily calculate the value of t by putting all these values in given  equations."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "If l=15, b=4, s=3, m=2 and t= 1. Find the value of v. l=length of the cutting stroke in mm, b=width of the work in mm, s=feed in mm, v=cutting speed in mm/minute, m=the ratio between return time to cutting time and t=machining time in minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.06",
            "b) 0.03",
            "c) 0.12",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l*b*(m+1) / (1000*v*s). From this equation, we can easily calculate the value of v by putting all mentioned values."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "If n=rpm of the bull wheel=2, l= length of the cutting stroke in mm=3mm and m= the ratio between return time to cutting time= 5. Then find the value of cutting speed in mm/minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3",
            "b) 0.36",
            "c) 0.15",
            "d) 0.18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: C.S. = n*l* (1+m) / 100. Here l=3mm, n=2, m=5. So by putting these values in the above equation we can easily get the answer as 0.36."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "If l=20, t=5, s=4, v=3 and m= 2. Find the value of b. l=length of the cutting stroke in mm, b=width of the work in mm, s=feed in mm, v=cutting speed in mm/minute, m=the ratio between return time to cutting time and t=machining time in minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 10000",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l*b*(m+1) / (1000*v*s). We can get the value of b by putting all mentioned values in the given equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "If t=0.10, b=5, s=4, v=1 and m= 2. Find the value of l. l=length of the cutting stroke in mm, b=width of the work in mm, s=feed in mm, v=cutting speed in mm/minute, m=the ratio between return time to cutting time and t=machining time in minute.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26.66",
            "b) 53.33",
            "c) 13.33",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the formula, t= l*b*(m+1) / (1000*v*s). We can get the value of l by putting all the values in the given equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Milling machine can hold______ cutters at a time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only one",
            "b) only two",
            "c) only three",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Milling machine is a machine tool that removes the metal as the work is fed against a rotating multipoint cutter. Here, in milling machine multi point cutter should be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Which of the following machine is superior to other machines as regards accuracy and better surface finish?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lathe",
            "b) drill",
            "c) shaper",
            "d) milling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It can be easily understood from its definition. This is the characteristic and advantage of milling cutters and that’s the reason why it is used more. "
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Which type of machining can be done by milling machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cutting keyways",
            "b) slots and grooves",
            "c) gears",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It can hold number of cutters at a time. Milling machine has multi point cutters."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Which of the following motion does a milling machine has?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical motion",
            "b) crosswise motion",
            "c) longitudinal motion",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lathe, drill and shaper are general purpose machines. They are versatile while milling machine is special purpose machine.Special purpose machine are always superior to general purpose machines for a particular specific work."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "The various milling process may be classified in ______ categories.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Various milling process may be classified in 2 categories: peripheral milling and face milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Upmilling and downmilling are the subtype of ________ milling process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) peripheral milling",
            "b) face milling",
            "c) both peripheral milling and face milling",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peripheral milling is the type of milling in which produced machine surface remains parallel to the axis of cutter."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Which of the following milling is known as conventional milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) both upmilling and downmilling",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Up milling is also known as conventional milling as in this process metal is removed by cutter which rotates in the opposite direction of the travel of the work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is also known as climb milling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) both upmilling and downmilling",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Down milling is also known as climb milling as in this process metal is removed by cutter which rotates in the same direction of the travel of the work piece."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "The thickness of the chip in upmilling is _______  at the beginning of the cut.",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimum",
            "b) maximum",
            "c) zero",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the working of the upmilling, at the begining the the thickness of chip is minimum as cutting force vary from zero to maximum in upmilling. So intially thickness of chip is minimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "The thickness of the chip in upmilling is _______ in when the cut terminates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimum",
            "b) maximum",
            "c) zero",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cutting force vary from zero to maximum in up milling. At the end due to maximum force chip thickness is high."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "The cutting force is directed _____ and this tends to lift the work from the fixture in upmilling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upward",
            "b) downward",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is false. The upmilling opertion is safe. This is the benefit of this process."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "The cutting action can be done from both sides of the table to finish the job. This is the advantage of _____ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the disadvantage of this process. The upmilling is feasible."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "More depth of cut can be used in ______milling process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the disadvantage of this process. The extra clamping forces may be required to fix the job on the table."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Difficulty is experienced in pouring coolant just on the cutting edge from where the chip begins. This is the disadvantage of______ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the disadvantage of upmilling. Use of cutting fluid is difficult in upmilling. "
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "The work is pulled by cutter teeth and hence the job may get spoiled or breakaway. This is the disadvantage of _____ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the disadvantage of downmilling.In downmilling, job and tool movements are in same direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "As the cutter progress, the chip accumulate at the cutting zone, spoils the work surfaces. This is the disadvantage of ______ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the disadvantage of upmilling. Cutter turns against the direction in which work is being fed."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Cutter teeth wears out soon as in the beginning itself the teeth comes in contact with the hard surface of the workpiece. This is the disadvantage of _______ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the disadvantage of downmilling. Cutter turns in similar direction in which the work is being fed."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "The burr on the surface cleans during the cutting operation. This is the advantage of _______ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is the advantage of downmilling. Its surface finish can be improved if it is free."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Upmilling is the process of removing metal by a cutter which is rotated _______   direction of the travel of the workpiece.",
        "Options": [
            "a) in the same",
            "b) against the",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the definition of upmilling process. This upmilling process is also known as conventional process."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Downmilling is the process of removing metal by a cutter which is rotated _______   direction of the travel of the workpiece.",
        "Options": [
            "a) in the same",
            "b) against the",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of downmilling process.This downmilling process is also known as climb milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "The thickness of  the chip is ______ when the tooth begins its cut in downmilling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum",
            "b) minimum",
            "c) zero",
            "d) can’t say anything"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cutting force vary from maximum to zero in downmilling so at the starting thickness of chip is maximum."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "The thickness of the chip is ______ when the cut terminates in downmilling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum",
            "b) minimum",
            "c) zero",
            "d) can’t say anything"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the working of downmilling, the cutting force vary from maximum to zero. So at the end thickness of chip is minimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "For downmilling, _______ machines are used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) light",
            "b) moderate",
            "c) rigid",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: Rigid machines are used in this process so that no clamping difficulty is there in downmilling."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Narrow slots can be milled in _________ milling process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upmilling",
            "b) downmilling",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the construction of this machine. This is done to make the forces strong enough on job to press down."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "In horizontal type universal column and knee type of milling machine, the table is placed on the knee-casting which in turn is mounted on the _____ slides of the main column.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) 45 degree inclined to both plans",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the construction of this machine. This is true for horizontal type machine. In plain and vertical type machine arrangement may be different."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "The knee is ______ adjustable on the column in horizontal column and knee type milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontally",
            "b) vertically",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The knee is vertically adjustable on the column in horizontal machine so that table can move in vertical direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "In this machine, the table can be moved ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) only up",
            "b) only down",
            "c) both up and down",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The table can be moved up and down to accommodate work of various heights."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "In this horizontal column and knee type machine, cutter rotates about _____ axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) 45 degree inclined to both plans",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this machine, cutter rotates about horizontal axis that’s the reason why it is known as horizontal column and knee type machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "The column and knee type milling machines are classified according to_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) various methods of supplying power to table",
            "b) different movements of table",
            "c) different axis of rotation of spindle",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per the classification of this machine, these are the aspects in which machine can be classified. These machines are mostly used in workshop."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "In a universal milling machine, table of the machine may be swiveled about a vertical axis, which helps in _____ milling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) helical",
            "b) cam",
            "c) both helical and cam",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It helps in helical milling, cam milling and several other milling. This universal milling is also suitable drilling and tapping. "
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Which of following part of these machines is swivel base?",
        "Options": [
            "a) top",
            "b) bottom",
            "c) middle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As per the construction of this machine, bottom part is swivel base on which stands the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Which part of this machine has transverse motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) top",
            "b) bottom",
            "c) middle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the construction of this machine,bottom parts has traverse motion. Bottom part can be moved toward or away from the column. "
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Which part of this machine has longitudinal motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) top",
            "b) bottom",
            "c) middle",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The top part of this machine has longitudinal motion in the guideways machined in the swivel base."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Guideways are machined on the _____ of the knee.",
        "Options": [
            "a) top",
            "b) middle",
            "c) bottom",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Guide ways are machined on the top of the knee. Guideways means a track or path along with something moves."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "Which of the following part of machine is a cross slide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) top",
            "b) middle",
            "c) bottom",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bottom part of machine is a cross slide. This part can move towards or away from the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "The knee is capable of being moved up and down over the guideways formed at the _____ of the column.",
        "Options": [
            "a) front",
            "b) back",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The top part of the machine means actual table and this table is located on the swivel base."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "The cutting edges are spaced ______ on the circumference of the cutter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) equally",
            "b) unequally",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cutting edges are spaced equally on the circumference of the cutter so as to provide an identical surface. If they are not spaced equally, then we can’e get a smooth surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "The milling cutters are revolving tools having ______ cutting edges.",
        "Options": [
            "a) only one",
            "b) only two",
            "c) only three",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It has one or several cutting edges depends upon its work.Different cutting edges are used for different purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "The cutting elements intermittently engages  ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) workpiece",
            "b) remove material",
            "c) both workpiece and remove material",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the definition of cutting elements, they can be termed as teeth which are used for the purpose of intermittent engagement."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Milling cutters are broadly classified into______ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both workpiece and removed material can intermittently engaged with the help of cutting elements through the principle of relative movements ."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Milling cutters may be made of______",
        "Options": [
            "a) high speed steel",
            "b) cemented tipped",
            "c) super high speed steel",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In milling cutters, intermittently engagement is done by relative motion of cutter and workpiece."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The cutters having a bore at center are mounted and keyed on a short shaft called_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) arbor",
            "b) shank",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Milling cutters broadly classified into 2 types : arbor type and shank type."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Arbor is connected with the milling machine spindle by_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) draw bolt",
            "b) driving bolt",
            "c) both draw bolt and driving bolt",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Milling matters are generally not made of ferrous cast alloys. Milling cutters may be made of non-ferrous cast alloys."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Slab mill cutter is an example of ______ milling cutter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) arbor type",
            "b) shank type",
            "c) special type",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slab mill is the milling which is mainly used for the purpose of rapid machining of large and broad surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Plain milling cutter is an example of ______ milling cutter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) arbor type",
            "b) shank type",
            "c) special type",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the classification of milling cutters. These cutters are used in applications such as tracer milling, profile milling and plunging "
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Side milling cutter is an example of ______ milling cutter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) arbor type",
            "b) shank type",
            "c) special type",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is categorized under special type. Flat surfaces can be milled by this cutter. Apart from it it can perform other some simple milling operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Slitting saw cutter is an example of ______ milling cutter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) arbor type",
            "b) shank type",
            "c) special type",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As per the classification of milling cutters. This cutter can handle deep and long open slots in a more comfortable manner, which increase the productivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Carbide and ceramic tips are used in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) slab mill",
            "b) face mill",
            "c) fly mill",
            "d) none of mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is type of special purpose because it is not used for removing lots of material. It is used for the purpose of cutting a narrow slit into material."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Slot drill consists of ______ flutes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both are almost similar. There is only one difference that ends of ball nose cutters are hemispherical.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "The indexing operation can also be adapted for producing ______ headed bolts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hexagonal",
            "b) square",
            "c) both hexagonal and square",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the definition of indexing.It is generally used for milling machine but it has also some application in boring,grinders, drill presses etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Indexing is accomplished by using a special attachment known as__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dividing head",
            "b) index head",
            "c) both dividing head and index head",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The indexing operation can also be adapted for producing hexagonal and square headed bolts. It is versatility of this method and that’s the reason why it is largely used."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "The dividing heads are of ____ types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:In cutting spur gear, equal spacing of teeth on the gear blank can be performed by indexing."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the type of dividing heads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plain dividing head",
            "b) universal dividing head",
            "c) optical dividing head",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Indexing head is also known as dividing head and this driving head is also known as indexing head."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "Which of the following dividing head is also known as simple dividing head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plain dividing head",
            "b) universal dividing head",
            "c) optical dividing head",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dividing heads are of 3 types: universal driving head, optical driving head and plain driving head."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most common type of indexing arrangement used in workshops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plain dividing head",
            "b) universal dividing head",
            "c) optical dividing head",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All plain driving head, universal driving head and optical driving head are the types of dividing heads."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the important part of universal head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) worm",
            "b) index plate",
            "c) sector arm",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Plain dividing head is also known as simple dividing head. It performs simple not too complicated tasks."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "Which of the following has single start threads in universal dividing head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) worm",
            "b) index plate",
            "c) sector arm",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the application of universal dividing head. It is very versatile and can perform various operation that’s why it is used in industry."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Rotation of spindle is done through _______ arrangement in universal dividing head.",
        "Options": [
            "a) worm",
            "b) worm wheel",
            "c) both worm and worm wheel",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the advantage of this head. Due to its versatility it can perform the tasks of other indexing methods and can execute all form of indexing."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "By linking the worm and worm gear driving mechanism of the attachment with the leadscrew of the table, continuous ______ motion can be imparted to the workpiece.",
        "Options": [
            "a) rotary",
            "b) transverse",
            "c) reciprocating",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Worm, sector arm, index plate, sector arch,sector ram, crank, taper hole, spindle etc. are the main parts of universal head ."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the method of indexing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) compound indexing",
            "b) differential indexing",
            "c) angular indexing",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All mentioned are the methods of indexing. Generally direct indexing is used but when the indexing required for numbers is beyond the the range of direct indexing, other methods are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Which of the following indexing method is also known as rapid indexing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) direct indexing method",
            "b) angular indexing method",
            "c) compound indexing method",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Direct indexing method is also known as rapid indexing method because it is more fast as compare to others."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "In direct indexing, the operation may be performed in_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) plain dividing head",
            "b) universal dividing head",
            "c) both plain and universal dividing head",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Simple indexing method is also known as plain indexing method, which is used for the simple task."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "The rapid index plate is generally fitted to the ______ end of the spindle nose.",
        "Options": [
            "a) front",
            "b) rear",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Direct indexing is used when a large number of identical pieces are indexed by very small divisions. It is generally not used when divisions are large"
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "In direct indexing, the plate has ______ equally spaced holes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 24",
            "c) 48",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:The operation may be performed in these both dividing head plain driving head and universal driving head."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "If n=number of divisions required, then find the number of holes to be moved in direct indexing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12/n",
            "b) 24/n",
            "c) 12*n",
            "d) 24*n"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the working of direct indexing, the worm and worm wheel are first disengaged. This is done in a manner similar to that used in the back gear of a lathe by turning a handle which operates an eccentric bushing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "If number of divisions required=4, then find the number of holes to be moved in direct indexing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 4",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The required number of divisions on the work is obtained by means of the rapid index plate, which is generally fitted to the front end of the spindle nose."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "The cutting tool used in shaper is a _______ point cutting tool.",
        "Options": [
            "a) single",
            "b) multi",
            "c) double",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is a single point cutting tool. For example, square nose tool, round nose tool etc. are the examples of the single point cutting tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "In a shaper, clearance is _______ to a lathe tool.",
        "Options": [
            "a) similar",
            "b) different",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shaper is mostly used with the purpose to machine straight, flat surfaces and for that it has rake."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Shaper tools are______",
        "Options": [
            "a) quite light",
            "b) moderate",
            "c) much more rigid",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Clearance is similar to lathe tool in shaper. Also some type of angles are also similar to lathe machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used to support the work on the table?",
        "Options": [
            "a) clamped in a vice",
            "b) clamped on the table",
            "c) both clamped in a vice and clamped on the table",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only some type of angles are similar in both machines. Tool angles are different in the case of shaper with respect to lathe."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is not used to support the work on the table?",
        "Options": [
            "a) clamped on the angle plate",
            "b) clamped on a V block",
            "c) held between shaper index centre",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shape tools are much more rigid in order to make it able to perform jobs nicely, without any slip and with more accuracy.."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Which of the following tool is not used in shaper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) right hand finishing tool",
            "b) square nose tool",
            "c) left hand side facing tool",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the working principle of this machine, this tools should be heavy so as to provide strength to it so that it can perform heavy jobs."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Right hand roughing tool is used in_______.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lathe",
            "b) shaper",
            "c) both lathe and shaper",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per the manufacturing of this machine, this machine is highly strong enough to withstand any shock."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Shaping can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vertical milling machines are of two types: bedmill and turrent mill and due to its construction features these vertical type milling machines can performed shaping easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "surfacing can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surfacing can be performed more effectively by vertical milling machine. This machine has a spindle. It rotates in vertical direction over the table."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Form cutting can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Form cutting can be performed more effectively by horizontal milling machine. The spindle in the horizontal milling machine is mounted on the horizontal arbor above table."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "Slab milling can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slab milling can be performed more effectively by horizontal milling machine. This slab mill is also used in gang milling."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Drilling can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In vertical milling, the workpiece is held by a horizontal table and this horizontal table rotates about a vertical axis. There are none-rotating tools which can be fed by crossrail and then drilling operation is performed which is more effective in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Boring can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vertical boring milling is more effectively as it has wide application in ring gear blanks, turbine casting and locomotive tires and so on."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "Dovetailing can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per the classification of milling operations. Dovetailing means joint something like link together with the help of dovetail. "
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Straddle milling can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sometimes we machine two or more vertical parallel surfaces at a single cut, this type of operation is known as straddle milling. Horizontal milling can perform it more nicely.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Angular milling can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Angular milling is a type of milling that mills flat surfaces which are neither parallel or perpendicular to the axis of milling cutter. It is performed more accurately by both milling machines: horizontal and vertical."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Cutting T-slots can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) can’t say anything",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This process depends upon the size of the T bolts which are going to be used and its typical milling process which can be performed by vertical milling more effectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Slotting can be performed more effectively by ______ milling machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) horizontal",
            "b) vertical",
            "c) both horizontal and vertical",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Slotting is the removal of material in the form of chips by a relative movement of a tool with a cutting edge relative to a workpiece along a non-circular trajectory."
    }
]